<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The pleasaunt historie of Lazarillo de Tormes a Spaniarde wherein is conteined his marueilous deedes and life. With the straunge aduentures happened to him in the seruice of sundrie masters. Drawen out of Spanish by Dauid Rouland of Anglesey.</title>
            <title>Lazarillo de Tormes. English</title>
            <author>Hurtado de Mendoza, Diego, 1503-1575.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1586</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 136 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05199</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15336</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109366</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845016</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845016</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9886</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05199)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9886)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 405:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The pleasaunt historie of Lazarillo de Tormes a Spaniarde wherein is conteined his marueilous deedes and life. With the straunge aduentures happened to him in the seruice of sundrie masters. Drawen out of Spanish by Dauid Rouland of Anglesey.</title>
                  <title>Lazarillo de Tormes. English</title>
                  <author>Hurtado de Mendoza, Diego, 1503-1575.</author>
                  <author>Rowland, David, fl. 1569-1586.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[128] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Abell Ieffes, dwelling in the fore streete without Crepell gate nere Groube streete at the signe of the Bell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1586.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of "Lazarillo de Tormes", a fictitious biography attributed to Diego Hurtado de Mendoza.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The Spaniardes life.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9886:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Pleaſaunt Hiſtorie of Lazarillo de Tormes a Spaniarde, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is conteined his mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueilous deedes and life.</p>
            <p>With the ſtraunge ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentures happened to him in the ſeruice of Iun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie Maſters.</p>
            <p>Drawen out of Spaniſh by Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid Rouland of Angleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y.</p>
            <p>Accuerdo, Oluid.</p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Abell Ieffes, dwelling in the fore ſtreete without Crepell gate nete Groube ſtreete at the ſigne of the Bell. 1586.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="printers_device">
            <pb facs="tcp:9886:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9886:2"/>
            <head>To the right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull Sir Thomas <hi>Greſſam Knight.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN I had read ouer this litle treatiſe (right worſhinful,) finding it for the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge and mery reports, very recreatiue &amp; pleaſant. I thought it no labor euill beſtowed, to occupie my ſelfe in the tranſlation thereof. And being moued thereto the rather, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing that in Fraunce many deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted therein, being turned into their tongue, I fully determined to bring my former pretence to end: Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that beſides much mirth, here is alſo a true diſcription of the nature &amp; diſpoſition of ſundrie Spaniards. So that by reading hereof, ſuch as haue not trauailed Spaine, may as well diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne
<pb facs="tcp:9886:3"/>much of the maners &amp; cuſtonis of that countrey, as thoſe that haue there long time continued. And being now finiſhed, I was ſo bold as to dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the fruite of my ſimple labor vnto your worſhip, who both for trauaile, dallie conference with diuers nations, and knowledge in al forein matters is knowen to be ſuch a one, as is well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to iudge, whether theſe reports of litle Lazaro be true or not. Wherfore I moſt humbly beſeech your worſhip fauorably to accept this poore preſent, (as offered of one) who wiſheth vnto you and yours, all health, wealth, long life, with increaſe of al veruſe &amp; vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: Truſting that after your vvaigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and important affaires, to caſe your tedious exerciſes, you vvill recreate your ſelfe vvith reading of ſome plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant part hereof.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worſhips moſt humbly to commanae, Dauid Rowland.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:9886:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Prologue of Lazaro de</hi> Tormes, vnto a Gentleman of Spaine, which was deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to vnderſtand the diſcourſe of his life.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am of opinion, that things ſo worthy of memory, peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture neuer heard of before, ne ſeene, ought by all reaſon to come abroad to the ſight of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, &amp; not be buried in the endleſſe pit of obliuio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, there perpetually to be forgotten: for it is poſſible that thoſe, which ſhal reade this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of my life, may finde ſome plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/> ſure therein. Wherfore true it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Plinie</hi> recordeth, <hi>there is no booke ſo euil, but hath ſome goodneſſe in it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained</hi> (conſidering all men taſt not a like,) that which one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> will not eate, another longeth ſore for: we
<pb facs="tcp:9886:4"/>ſee many deſpiſe things which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do greatly eſteine: Therefore nothing ought to be broken a caſt away, vnles it were deteſtable, but that firſt diuers men ſhould ſee the ſame, &amp; eſpecially being not hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but rather able, in fleade o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, to yeeld profite &amp; vtdi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie. If the worlde verre otherwiſe, very fewe would take penne in hand to pleaſure one man only, ſeing that they can not bring their workes to ende without great trauell: And when they haue ended their labor, they rightfully deſire to be recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penced, &amp; not with money, but only that all men with curteous m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de will trad and allow their workes, (yea &amp; if there be cauſe why) giue them praiſe. For to this ende <hi>Tullie</hi> ſaith, <hi>Honor doth mainteine art of cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi> Do you thinke that the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier that firſt mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth on the wall with his ladder, is wery of his li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e?
<pb facs="tcp:9886:4"/>No ſurely, the deſire of honour en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courageth him, ſo to venture into ſuch danger. So likewiſe in Arte and learning, we vſe to ſay, maſter Doctor hath preached wel, he is a man that ſeketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> health of ſouls: but I pray you dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of him whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he wilbe offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, that one ſhal ſay, O how diuinely you haue prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched maſter Doctor. The like hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth in me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of armes, as men co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly report, O how ſuch a knight iuſtled noughtly, and notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding he hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his coate armor to a Ieſter which commended him for running well, what would hee haue giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if he had ſaid the truth? Wherefore nowe that all thinges paſſe after ſuch a ſort, I confeſſing my ſelfe to bee no holier than my neighbours, am content that ſuch as finde any taſte in this my groſſe Stile and noueltie, may pleaſure and delight themſelves therwith:
<pb facs="tcp:9886:5"/>and they may perceius how a man liueth, after ſo many fortunes, daungers, and aduerſities.</p>
            <p>Therfore now I beſeech your wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhip, receiue with willing hart this poore token of my true affection, which ſhuld haue bene much richer if power &amp; abilitie had bene equall with deſire. And ſeeing that you haue commanded me to write the matter at length, I haue thought good not to begin the midſt of my life, but firſt to tel you of my birth, that al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may haue ful knowledge of my perſon, that thoſe which poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe great rents &amp; reuenues, may vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d what ſmall praiſe is due vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſeeing that Fortune hath deall parcially with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and how much comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dation they deſerue, which in deſpite of cruell fortune, with force &amp; induſtrie, by rowing out of tempeſinous ſeas, haue ariued to fortunate and happie ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tis.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:9886:5"/>
            <head>Lazaro declareth his life, and whoſe ſonne he was.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our worſhip ſhal vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande before all things, that my name is <hi>Lazaro de Tormes,</hi> ſon of <hi>Thome Gonſales</hi> and <hi>Antona Petes</hi> natiue of <hi>Teſſiares,</hi> a vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage neer <hi>Salamanka:</hi> I was borne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the riuer called <hi>Tormes,</hi> wherof I toke my ſurname, as hereafter you ſhal heare; my father whome God pardon, had the charge of a Mill ſtauding vpon that Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer wherein he ſupplied the roome of a Milner about rv yéeres. It fortuned on a night my mother bring gret with childe, was there brought to bed, and then was I borne: therefore nowe I may truly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the Riuer it ſelfe to be the place of my natiuitie: &amp; after the time I came to the age of eight yeares, there was layds to my Fathers charge that he had ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully cut the ſeames of mens ſacks that came thither to grind, wherefore he was taken and impriſoned, and being torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:9886:6"/>he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed the whole matter, denying nothing wherefore he was perſecuted. I truſte in God that he is now in paradiſe, ſeeing that the Goſpel doth ſay, that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are ſuch as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe their faults. About y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame time an army was made againſt the Turkes, &amp; my father being then ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for the miſhap aforeſaid, chanced to be one ſupplying the roume of a Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litor, vnder a knight which went thither, in whoſe ſeruice like a true and a faithful man, he ended his life. My mother being then a comfortleſſe widowe, after the loſſe of hir deare huſband, determined to inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite among ſuch as were vertuous &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, to be of that number, and therefore came immediatly to this noble Citie, where after that ſhee had hired a little houſe, ſhée kept an ordinarie table for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Students, and waſhed ſhyrts for a rompany of horſekepers, belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging to the Commander of <hi>Magdalona,</hi> by meanes whereof ſhe had accuſation to make often reſort vnto the ſtables, where in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of time, a black Morrien, one of maſter Commanders men, became to be famiarly acquainted with hir<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So that
<pb facs="tcp:9886:6"/>for his part hee would oftentimes arriue at midnight to our houſe, and returne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine betimes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morning, other whiles at noonetide, dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding at the dore, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my mother had egges to ſell, and ſo come in pretely without ſuſpection: At the beginning I was right ſorie to ſee him make repare thither, being afraid to behold his black vncomly viſage: but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that I once perceiued how only by his reſort our fare was ſo well amended, I could by no means finde in my heart to hate him, but rather beare him good will, reioycing to ſee him: for hee alwayes brought vs home with him good rounde can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s of breade, and pieces of broken meate, and in the Winter time wood to warme vs withall. To bee ſhort, by his continuall repaire thither, matters went ſo forwarde, that my mother founde good time to bring forth a yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g morren, whom I daily playde withall, and ſometimes helped to warme. And I remember very well, that on a time as my Stepfather played merily with his yong ſonne, the little childe perceiuing that my mother and I ware whyte, and his father
<pb facs="tcp:9886:7"/>blacke as yeat, he ran away for feare to my mother, and ſtretching foorth his fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, cried <hi>Mamma</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hugge: Wherat my blacke ſtepfather would laugh, and ſay, a whoreſon, art thou afrayce of thy father? Although I was then but yong, I right wel marked the childs words, and ſaid to my ſelf, ther are many ſuch in the world, which do abhor and flée from others by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they cannot ſee what ſhape they haue themſelues. Within a while after, it pleaſed fortune that the daily co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Aide</hi> (for ſo was my fathers name) came to the cares of him that was Stewarde to maſter Commander, who made ſuthſtreight inquirie, that he was aduertiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> how the black moren did vſe to ſteale halfe the prouander that was allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> horſes, yea, horſecouerings, ſhetes and curry combes, other whiles wood, &amp; bran: which things in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>éede he alwayes ſaid were loſt,
<note place="margin">All was fiſh that came to the nette.</note> &amp; when nothing could bee gotten to ſerue his turne, he would neuer ſlicke to vnſhoe the horſes, to get ſome gaine, preſenting daily all ſuch giftes to my mother, as a help to bring vp my litle blacke brother. Let vs neuer therefore
<pb facs="tcp:9886:7"/>maruell more at thoſe which ſteale from the poore, nor yet at them which conuey from the houſes they ſerue, to preſente therewith whome they loue, in hope to attayne thereby their deſired pleaſure, ſeeing that loue was able to encourage this poore bondman or ſlaue to doe thus much as I haue ſaide, or rather more, which by euident triall was afterwards proued true: for I being examined of the déede, after much thretning was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as a childe, for feare,
<note place="margin">There is an order in that countrey when any Moredoth commirte any hemous effe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to ſtrip himna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and being bound with his hands and his knees to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, to baſt him with hote droppes of bur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning Larde.</note> ſo diſcouer the whole matter, confeſſing howe I had ſolde certaine horſeſhoowes to a ſmith at my mothers co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement: wherfore my miſerable ſtepfather was by iudgement of the law, as the order is there, whipped and Larded, and to my mother expreſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement was giuen vpon the vſual paine of a hundreth ſtripes, no more to enter into the houſe of the aboue named Commander, nor yet entertaine into hirs the vnfortunate <hi>Zaide.</hi> My ſorrowefull mother fearing to throwe the helue after the hatchet, determined by all meanes to kéepe their commaundement, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhee entred into ſeruice with thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:9886:8"/>which at that time dwelte at the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ric Inne called <hi>Solona,</hi> ſo to eſcape dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger &amp; to auoyde the dangerous reports of euill tongues, where ſhee ſuffered much ſorrowe, and there brought vp my blacke brother, until he was able to run abrode, and that I being a good ſtripling,
<note place="margin">There is no pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſion there in Innes: for the gueſtes muſt ſende a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brode into the towne for all ſuch yittell as they neede.</note> coulde go vp and down the town to prouide the gueſtes of wine, and candels, and other things neceſſarie. In this meane tyme, there happeued a blind man to come thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to lodge, who thinking me to be a fit ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to leade him, deſired my mother that I might ſerue him, wherewith ſhe being right wel content, moſt earneſtly prayed him to be good maſter vnto me, becauſe I was an honeſt mans ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nne, who in maintaining the faith of Ieſus Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Lurkes, died in the battel of <hi>Gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues,</hi> &amp; howe that ſhe truſted in almightie God I would proue as honeſt a man as he: therfore in any wiſe that he would be careful ouer me, being a fatherleſſe child. Let me alone then (anſwered he) I will not vſe him as a ſeruaunte, but as a ſonne. Then in happie time I began to ſerue my olde and newe maiſter: And
<pb facs="tcp:9886:8"/>after we had remained certaine dayes at <hi>Salamanka,</hi> my blind maſter perceiuing his gaine there to he but ſmall, determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to departe thence: and a little before our departure, I went to ſee my mother: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I came wher ſhe was, we ſhed both moſte bitter teares, and ſhe gaue mée hir<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> bleſſing, ſaying, nowe my deare ſonne I ſhal ſee thee no more, therfore be a good childe, I pray God bée thy helpe, I doe thanke the Lord I haue brought thée vp well hitherto, and I haue nowe put thee to a good maſter, from henceforth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for thy ſelfe, ſéeing that I haue done my part. I tooke my leaue and retour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in haſte to my maſter, which taried for me ready to take his voyage. So wée departed out of <hi>Salamanka,</hi> and came on our way as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rre as the bridge, at the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſtandeth a beaſt of Stone, faſhioned much like a bul: as ſone as we came nere it, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blindma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> willed me to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche, ſaying <hi>Lazaro,</hi> put thine eare to this Bull, and thou ſhalt heare a terrible noiſe within it: as ſoone as he had ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> words, I was ready like a foole to bowe down my head, to be as he had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded,
<pb facs="tcp:9886:9"/>thinking that his wordes had bene moſt true: but the traiterous blind man ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting how neare it my head was, thru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth forth his arme vpon a ſod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ne, with ſuch force, that my fore head tooke ſuch a blowe againſt the diueliſh Buil, that for the ſpace of three dayes my head feſte the paines of his hornes, wherefore he was right glad &amp; ſaide: Conſider nowe what thou art thou fooliſh calle, thou muſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that the blind mans boy ought to knowe one tricke more than the dinel himſelf. It ſemed then immediatly that I awaked out of ſimplicitie, wherein I had of long time ſlept (like a child,) &amp; I ſaw to my ſelf, my blind maſter hath good reaſon, it is ful time for me to open mine eyes, yea &amp; to prouide &amp; ſeeke mine owne aduantage co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſſdering y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>alone with out any helpe. We continued on our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, &amp; within fewe dayes I came to good knowledge, ſo he perceiuing what a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy tong I had, was right glad, &amp; ſaid, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gold nor ſiluer can I giue thée, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, I doe meane to teach thée y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way to liue, and ſo certainly he did: for next after God he made me a man, and although he
<pb facs="tcp:9886:9"/>was blinde, it was he that gaue me light and that taught mée howe to knowe the world<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. I reioyce to declare vnto your worſhip theſe Childiſh toyes, that you may ſee how comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dable it is for a man of low eſtate to bee brought to authoritie and exalted, and contrariwyſe what a ſhame it is, a man for dignitie and eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation to bée pulled downe to wretched miſerie, But to retourne to my blynde maſter, and to ſhew his nature, I aſſure you that ſith the beginning of the worlde God neuer made man more deceitfull and craftie: for in his art and trade of liuing he far paſſed all other: he could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite by hart a hundred long prayers and moe, yea, &amp; the life of all the holy ſaincts: at his deuotion time he vſed ſuch a loude tunable voy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that it might be heard tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughout the Churche where hée praied, and beſides all that, he could counferſet a good deuoute countenance in praying, without any ſtrange geſture, either with mouth or eye, as other blinde are accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to vſe. I am not abl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to recite a thouſand other manner of wayes which hée had to get money: hée would make
<pb facs="tcp:9886:10"/>many beleeue that he had praiers fo Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers good purpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, as for to make wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men bring foorth children, yea, and to make men to loue their wiues, although they had hated the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before neuer ſo much. He would prognoſticate to women that were with childe, whether they ſhould bring foorth a Sonne or a daughter: in matters of Phyſicke, hee woulde affirme that <hi>Galen</hi> neuer knew halfe ſo much as hee: alſo for any griefe, the tooth ach, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye other diſeaſe, there was neuer one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plained, but that immediatly he would ſay, do this, doe that, ſeeth ſuch an herbe, take ſuch a roote: So that by this his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>actiſe, he had daily great reſorte made vnto him, (eſpecially of women) which did faithfully beleeue all that euer he ſaid: by them hee had great gaine, for he wan more in a moneth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty of his occupation did in a whole yeere. Yet for all his daily gaines, you muſt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that there was neuer man ſo wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched a inggarde. For hee cauſed mée not onely to die for hunger, but alſo to wante what ſo euer I nee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d. And therefore to confeſſe the troth, if I had not founde out
<pb facs="tcp:9886:10"/>meanes to helpe my ſelfe, I had bene bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried long ſithence. Wherfore oftentimes I would ſo preuent him of all his crafte, that my portion ſhoulde proue as good as his: and to bring my matter ſo to paſſe, I vſed wonderfull deceits (wherof I will recite vnto you ſome) although ſomtimes my practiſing of them did coſt mee bitter paines. This bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd man caried alwayes his bread and his vittell in a little bag of cloth, which was ſhutte at the mouthe with an Iron buckle, vnder a miſerable locke and keye: at the time of putting his meate in, and taking it out, he would kéepe ſuch ſtraight account, that all the world was not able to deceiue him of one crun me, and therefore there was no helpe, but that I muſt néedes bee content with that ſmall allowance that hée gaue mee, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>wares I was ſure to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch at two morſels: and as ſone as euer he had ſhut his little lock, he wold thinke then that all were ſure, imagining that I had other matters in hand: then would I boldely vnrip and ſowe vp againe the ſyde of his couetous ſacke, vſing daily to launce one of the ſides, there to take
<pb facs="tcp:9886:11"/>out not onely bread at mine owne plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but alſo ſitces of fleſh, and ſweete ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>banades: So that by ſuch meanes I found conuenient time to eaſe the raging hunger which he was cauſe of. Morcouer all the maney that ruer I could conuey &amp; ſteale from him, I changed alwayes into halfe blanks and when any man deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded any praier, he had always of ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie a blanke giuen him for his hire, &amp; bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he could not ſee, it ſhould be deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red mee: but he could neuer ſo ſoone put foorth his hand to receiue it, but I was as readie to throwe it into my mouth, and by quicke erchaunge to giue him the iuſt value of halfe of it, whercat hee woulde much murmure, knowing by the onely feeling of it what it was, and would ſay: How in the diuels name cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eth it that ſithence thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to me, I receiue but halfe blankes, and before I had alwayes a whole blanke and ſometimes two? I thinke ſurely that thy vnluckineſſe be cauſe thereof. From that time forwards her thought good to ſhorten his prayers, cutting them off in the middeſt: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded me, that as ſoone as the
<pb facs="tcp:9886:11"/>almes giuer had turned his back. I ſhold plucke him by the cloake.
<note place="margin">Blind men ſtand there in Churche por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ryady to be hired for money to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite any prayer</note> Then ſtreight wayes changing tune, he would begin to crie with loude voice (as blindmen vſe to do) who will heare ſuch a deuout prayer, or elſe the life of ſome holie Sainct? At dinner or ſupper time, hee had alwayes before him a little potfull of wine, which oftentimes I woulde laye hande on, and after two or three kiſſes ſende it him ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretely home againe: But that happie time continued but a while, for I was wont to leaue ſo little behinde mée, that he might ſoone eſpie the faulte, as in deeds immedially hee did miſtruſt the whole matter, wherefore hee began a newe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, not to leaue his wine anie more at randon, but to auoyde daunger, had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes his little pot faſt by the eare, ſo to be ſure of his drinke. Yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for all this, the Adamant ſtone had neuer ſuch vertue to drawe Iron to it, as I had to ſucke vp his wine with a long réede which I had prepared for the purpoſe: for at ſoone as the ende of my reede had bene once in, I might well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire hun to fill the pot againe. Yet at the
<pb facs="tcp:9886:12"/>laſte the craftie blinde man chaunced to feele mee, and being angrie, determined to take an other way, to place his pot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne his legges, couering it ſtill with his hande, ſo to auoy call former daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers: when hee had ſo done, I being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to drinke wyne, did long to taſte of it, and perceiuing that my reede coulde then no more preuaile at all, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed an other kinde of fetche, howe to make a hole in the bottome of his wine po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and to ſtoppe the ſame with a little ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fte ware, ſo that at dynner time ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a ſhewe as I were readie to dye for colde, I would créepe betweene th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> blynd mans legges, to warme my ſelfe at his ſmall fire, by the heate whereof, the wax being little in quantitie, woulde ſo melte away, that the wyne woulde iſſue down into my meuth freſhely and trime. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſure to gape vpward ſo iuſt that one droppe ſhould n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uer fall beſide. So that when my blinde maſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r woulde taſte of his wine, hee ſhoulde neuer finde drop to oue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch his thurſt, wherat he would much maruell, cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſing and ſwering all maner of othes, yea wiſhing the pot and all that
<pb facs="tcp:9886:12"/>was within it at the druell, muſing ſtill how his wine ſhould bee ſo conſumed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. Then ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ightwayes to excuſe my ſelfe. I would ſay, I truſt you will not miſtruſt m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e gentle vucle, ſeeing that the pot came neuer out of your owne hands. Wherevpon then to be well reformed of the truthe, he began to feele and to gro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the pot ouer ſo o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ten, that at laſt he found the ſpring, and at that time diſſembled quietly the matter, as if hee had percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued nothing. The next day I beganne agayne to prepare my ſelfe after my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed ſorte to take my pleaſure of his wine, being ignoraunt of the euill that ſhould enſue, thinking that my maiſter would neuer haue miſtruſted mee about ſuch a matter, wherfore I was mery and careleſſe. But my cruell maſter, percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing after what ſtraunge ſort I receiued thoſe ſweete drops of wine, which came foorthe as a quicke ſpring at his potte bottome, my face bent towards heauen, my eyes in manner cloſed, ſo to receius with more delight and better taſte, that pleaſant licour which I thought did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue my life, the malitious blynde
<pb facs="tcp:9886:13"/>man hauing time of rouengement at his will, Inted vp the ſweete and ſoure pot, (as I may ſaye,) and with all his force clapped it ſo rudely vpon my face, that I thought varily heauen abeue, and all therein, had fallen vpon mee. The cruell blowe was ſuch that it tooke away my ſenſes, it troubled ſore my braines, and my face was all cut with pieces of the broken potte, yea, and ſome of my teeth were then broken, which as yet is ſeene, wherefore I neuer loued him after, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit be cheriſhed me daily: yet for al the falſe loue and fridſhip which he ſhewed, I perceiued right well how glad hee was that he had ſo puniſhed mee. To make me amendes, he waſhed with wine the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des which the vnhappie pot had made, &amp; after much l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ughing, ſaide, what ſayeſt thou to this my boy, the wy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that hath done the hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t ſhall now heale thee again, and ſuch other merie ieſtes, which I vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ked. As ſoone as I began to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that my face was in manner heal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, &amp; conſidered with my ſelfe, howe that with fewe more ſuch blowes, the blinte m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n might quickely vring mee to
<pb facs="tcp:9886:13"/>my graue: And therefore determined to ſhorten his dayes if I coulde, which thing I went not about immediatly, but taried a due time for mine owne ſafetis and aduantage. And whereas af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes I went about to ſorget mine anger, and to forgiue him the blowe, the cuill vſage and entertainement which hee daily ſhewed me, woulde in no wiſe conſent thereto. For ſtill hee tormented me with ſore blowes without any offence or faulte at all. And when any man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded why he handled me ſo cruelly, ſtraight wayes he woulde vp and declare the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſcourſe of his pot, ſaying, do you not thinke that this childe is ſome innocent, and alwayes at the ende of his tale theſe would be his words: who vnleſſe it were the deuill him ſelfe could haue found out ſuch rare prankes? The people woulde much maruell at my muention, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing themſelues, would ſay vnto my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter: Puniſh him, Puniſh him, God will rewarde you therefore: which thing hee did continually, &amp; would haue done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their bidding: wherefore I daily led him through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worſt wayes I could find
<pb facs="tcp:9886:14"/>poſſibly all for verie ſpite, minding if I could to doe him harme: where I might cipye ſtones or myre, I woulde euen through the thickeſt: &amp; although I could neuer eſcape drie foote, I was glad with loſing one of mine owne eyes, to put out both his that neuer hadde any.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e was borne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>inde.</note> At ſuch times of his ſorrowes to bée reuenged, he woulde take holde with his nailes on the hinder parte of my heade, where with his often pulling, hee had lefie very fews haires behinde: it would neuer preuaile me then to ſay, that I could finde no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter way, nor yet to ſweare how I did not leade him that naughty way maliciouſly for he was ſo ſubtile that to my words he woulde giue ſmall credite. But nowe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe your worſhip ſhal vnderſtand how farre his crafte did extende. I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare one chaunce amongſt many, which happened in the time I ſerued him wher in he ſeemeth to giue full vnderſtanding of his ſubtiltie: When wee departed out of <hi>Salamanka,</hi> his intente was to come to the Citie of <hi>Toledo,</hi> knowing that the people were richer there than in other places, although not ſo charitable, yet
<pb facs="tcp:9886:14"/>for all that, leaning to his olde pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe: <hi>More giueth the niggarde than the naked,</hi> we tooke our voyage through the beſt villages wee coulde finde, where we found great gain and profit, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after ſuch ſorte a certayne time: and where as wee liked not our entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the third day we would be ſure to take our leaue and to ende our yeere. It fortuned at the laſt, that we arrined to a towne which is called <hi>Almorx,</hi> at ſuch time as they gathered their grapes, wher one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> viniar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gaue my maſter a whole bunche, which by reaſon of the late time, were more than ripe, ſo that ſome were ready to fall from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unch: wherfore he could by no meanes carie it in his bagge, by reaſon it was ſo moyſt. Therefore he determined to make a ſumptuous ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket with it, partely becauſe hee hadde no meanes to carie it with him, and partly becauſe hée thought therewith to pleaſe me, which hadde receiued that day many cruell blowes. As ſoone as we founde a valley fitte for the purpoſe, wée ſatte vs downe, and my maſter ſaid, <hi>Lazaro</hi> my boy, I will nowe vſe a great liberalitie
<pb facs="tcp:9886:15"/>towards thee, it is my pleaſure that both of vs ſhall eate friendly together this bunch of grapes, whereof thy part ſhall be as much as mine, we will part it after this ſort, thou ſhalt take one grape and I an other, promiſing me faithfully that thou wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not take aboue one at a time, and I will doe the like to thee, and ſo we will quietly ende our bunche, without any fraude or guile on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ither part. Vpon that condition we agreed and began our bancket: but my maſter belike forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>miſe, did ſoone chaunge pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, for immediatly hée began to picke the grapes by two &amp; two, thinking per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture that I would do the like, as he might well thinke. In deede I was not farre behinde him, for as ſoone as I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teiued that hee had broken the lawe, I was not content to goe by two and two as he did, but went before him, taking vp by two and thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> together, and ſometime more as I was beſt able. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bunch was ended, he tooke the ſtalke in his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and wagging his head ſaid, <hi>Lazaro</hi> thou haſt deceiued me, by God thou haſt eaten by three and three: I vtterly denied it,
<pb facs="tcp:9886:15"/>and ſaide, in déede vnckle it is not true: why ſhould you thinke ſo? Then he like a craftie blindman anſwered, I did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue ſtraight wayes h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>we the matter went, for when I began to take vp by two &amp; two, thou neuer didſt finde faulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>but didſt keepe ſilence. I then laughed to my ſelfe, although I was but young, I conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dered well his diſcrete conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir to auoide long talke, I will leaue apart many matters as well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant as worthy to bee noted, which haue fortuned to me with this my firſt maſter. I will onely tell what hapned a litle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I departed: we came to <hi>Scalona,</hi> a towne of the Dukes, and when we were at our lodging,
<note place="margin">Here they vſe fewe gridiròs but all ſpits, &amp; do roſt ouerth wart the coles. A mareuedi, is the ſixt part of an Engliſh peny.</note> hee gaue mee a piece of a ſauſedge to roſt, the which being almoſt inough, and the fat dropped and preſſed out vpon thin flices of bread, as the faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, and thoſe being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aten, hée drewe his purſe, and boldly drewe out a <hi>Mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uedi,</hi> willing me to fetch the value therof in wine. The deuill (who as they ſay) is the occaſion that men become thieues, was ready at hand to prepare opportuni, tie to deceiue him. It fortuned that neare
<pb facs="tcp:9886:16"/>the fire there lay a little roote, ſomewhat long and euill fauoured, ſuche a one as belike, was not leru <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able for the potte, and therefore was lefte there as abiecte: and as at that time there was no moe but hee and I alone, I felt my ſelfe pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with a lickorous appetite, my teeth beeing ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t on edge with the ſweete ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure of his roſted ſauſege, the which was the onely witneſſe that I ſhoulde bee the eater thereof) I not regarding what the ſeque<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e might bee, ſeauing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide all manner of feare, for to fulfill my raſh deſire, in the meane while that the blinde man was drawing his purſſe, I whipps off quickely the ſauſedge from the ſpitte, and thereon broached the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaide worme eaten roote, which my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter moſt willingly tooke and beganne to tourne, thinking to roſte that which for the goodneſſe, was not worthy t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bee boyled.</p>
            <p>So I wente for wine, and by the way I made a faire ende of my ſauſedge, and as ſoone as I came in againe, I founde my maſter wringing betwéene two ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of bread, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> naughtie roote, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:9886:16"/>what it was: for with his fingers he had not as yet touched it. Immediatly af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter he began to eate, taking a large bit of his bread, meaning to haue taſted a little of his ſauſedge, but his teeth entred into the roote, where he found a colde morſell: whereat hee being ſore abaſhed, ſhewed it to me, and ſaid, <hi>Lazaro</hi> what meaneth this? I then aunſwered: Nowe Ieſus what is this? Alas wretche that I am, doe you meane to blame me, you knowe well that I came but nowe from the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne with wine, ſurely ſome naughtie man hath bene here, that hath done this in deſpite or mockage. No no, then ſaide he, that cannot be poſſible, for I neuer let the ſpitte goe ſithence out of mine owne handes. Then to cleare my ſelfe, I began to ſweare all othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that I was innocent of that vile excha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge: but al was in vaine, for from the ſubtiltie of that vngratious blinde man, nothing could be kept hidde. Hee roſe vppe and tooke faſte holde on my heade, to ſmell whether hee coulde feele the ſauoure of his ſauſedge: and as ſoone as euer hee felte occaſion to ſuſpecte that I had eaten it, he was as gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e as a
<pb facs="tcp:9886:17"/>good bloud hound<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that had his chaſe in the winde: Wherefore to bée better en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmed of the trueth, being ſore indued with anger, he raſhely opened my mouth with the ſtrength of his handes, ſo that perforce I was fayns to gape euen to the vttermoſte: and then hée thruſteth in all haſte, into my mouth, his wormeaten noſe, which was both long and ſharpe, yea, which at that time by reaſon of great anger, was lengthned a long hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſo that the pike thereof did ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my throte. Wherefore, partely by reaſon of the feare that I was in, and partly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſedge in ſuch ſhort time was not ſetled in my ſtomacke, but moſt of all, by reaſon of the greate trouble which his monſtrous noſe put mée too, wherewith I was in a manner choked, I was forced to diſcouer my gluttonte, ſo that the ſauſedge of neceſſitie retour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to his olde maſter againe: for my poore ſtomacke was ſo much altered, that before the blynde man had drawen out his hoggiſh noſe, I was euen ready to render vp the theft. For looke as ſoone as euer hee hadde pulled out his ſnoute,
<pb facs="tcp:9886:17"/>the euil eaten ſauſedge came guſhing cut after, in honeſt companie. O mightie God howe ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> beene then buried, might well haue looked for my companie, for &amp; was altogether dead: his rage was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo great, that if men had not c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me in, I thinke certainely hee woulde haue taken away my life. With muche a doe I got me out of his handes, leauing him with his clawes full of that ſmall quantitie of heare which I had lefte, (all which tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he moſt iuſtly deſerued ſeeing that through his naughtineſſe I ſuffered ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h perſecution.) The vngodly blinde man, woulde then declare to as many as came in, my vnfortunate diſgraces, rehe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſing often ouer, as well the tale of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>otte, and of the bunch of gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pes, as alſo this laſt tricke of his ſauſedge. The laugh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> that men made was ſo great, that a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuch as were in the ſtreate came in to ſee the feaſte, where hée recited with ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all my miſaduentures, that mée thought verily, I did them greate wrong in not laughing for companie. When all this was paſt, there came to my minde a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine faint and a ſtouthfull cowa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="7 letters">
                  <desc>〈7 letters〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:9886:18"/>which I had committed, in not leauing him noſſeleſſe, ſeeing that I had time fit for the purpoſe: yea and that I had gone halfe the way to doe it. For if I had but cloſed my téeth together, his noſe had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner gone more abrode: &amp; truely I beléeue becauſe it was the noſe of that naughtie ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it would haue better agréed with my ſtomacke, than the ſauſedge did, for had it once beene inuiſible, I mighte well haue denied it him againe. Nowe I would to God my téeth had done their parte, for it had beene better ſo then otherwiſe. The hoſtiſe, &amp; other that were there, made vs friendes, and with the wine which I had brought for his ſupper, they waſhed my face, &amp; my throte, which his nayles had al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>torne. Wherat he made much grudging, ſaying, certainely this boy doeth conſume mée more wine in a yéere, with waſhing his woundes, than I do drinke in two. Without doubt <hi>Lazaro,</hi> thou arte more bounde to wine, than to thy father, for hée onely begot thée once, &amp; it hath ſaued thy life a thouſande times, and ſo declared howe many times hee had wounded mée and healed me againe with wine, &amp; then
<pb facs="tcp:9886:18"/>ſaid again: I promiſe thée truely <hi>Lazaro</hi> if any man in the world ſhal haue happy chaunce with wine, it is thou. Which woordes cauſed thoſe that were there, to laughe heartily, I being ſtill in moſte ſorowfull diſpaire. But looke what the blinde man prognoſticated then, it was not all in vayne, for his ſayings at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time proued afterwarde moſte true: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I haue oftentimes ſithence called to minde his wordes, whereby it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that he had a great gift in prophecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and therefore it hath often repented me of my cruell dealing towards him, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though his deſerts were euill, ſéeing that his wordes of Prophecie proued ſo true, as hereafter your worſhip ſhall plainely vnderſtande. To conclude, his euill na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and my vſage conſidered, I deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to forſake him for euer, and as I imagined daily thereuppon, deſirous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o departe, this his laſt déede perſwaded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> fully thereunto, and the matter chaunced to fall out thus: Within two dayes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, wée wente through the Citie to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde mennes charities, where it had rained much the might before, &amp; becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:9886:19"/>like wiſe it rayn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay, my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter wente praying vnder certaine por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> are th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, where it wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the raine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Lazaro,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> is Without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, for the more that nigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, the more earneſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> let vs draw <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>war<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to our lodging. But as it chaunced, we had vetweene vs and home, a great wyde gutier which the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vncle, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er is very bro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de and ſvnſte, ſo that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſhall haue muche a doe to paſſe, notwithſtanding. I haue new eſpied one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> were we may well ſeape ouer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> thought vertly then, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat I had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and therefore ſaid, my good boy, nowe I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> arte wiſe, I muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> thee leade <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> place, where I may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt eſcape a for nowe in winter it is not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to take water, eſpecially to goe wet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood. O how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lad I was then to ſee the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> I had wiſhed for, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herefore without delay, I brought him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vnder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ath the portal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, &amp; leade him
<pb facs="tcp:9886:19"/>right againſt a grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtoode<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> vncle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> place of all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> himſelfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> his vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> time of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> canſte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> take my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ump <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> leape <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> I could and too<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> poſte, as one that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ncounter of a Bull, and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> If <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vncle leape boldly as far as you can poſſibly, for elſe you may chaunce wet your ſelfe. I had not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaid the word, but that inc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently the poore blinde man was ready to take his race, returning a pace or two back<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſtanding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and ſo with great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> tooke his leape, throwing for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>war<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that at the
<pb facs="tcp:9886:20"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt his head tooke ſuch a mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrous blow againſt the cruell ſtonie pill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, that his head ſounde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> withall as it had bene a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bottell, wherevpon he ſell back with his clouen pate, hal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e dead: then gaue I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> leape and ſaide; howe now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould you ſmell the ſau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dge ſo well, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> not the piller I p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay you? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> a little what you can doe. So I le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te him there betwéene the handes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that came in all haſt to helpe him, &amp; tooke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ready waye ſtraight towardes the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owne gate, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> flow pace, and then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rotte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> forward, that before night I ariued to <hi>Tortois.</hi> After that ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> I neuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ought to knowe what God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> with him.</p>
            <p>(<g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>)</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:9886:20"/>
            <head>How Lazaro placed him ſelfe, with a Prieſt, and what thing hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to him in his ſeruice.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE nexte day after doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of mine owne ſafetie there. I departed thence and went to a village which is called <hi>Mekeda,</hi> where I met for my ſinnes, with a prieſt, who as ſoone as he eſpied how that I demaunded al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, did enquire whether I could helpe to maſſe: I aunſwered, ſaying, yes ſir, that I can, as truth it was: for although the blindman had vſed me ſcarce well, he taught me to do a thouſand feates, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of this was one. The Prieſt receiued me for his owne: ſo I eſcaped then front the thunder and came into the tempeſt, yea and God knoweth, howe from euill, to ten times worſe, for the blynde man was in compariſon of this maſter, a great <hi>Alexander.</hi> Howbeit, hee was ſo couetous a nigarde, as heretofore I haue rehearſed. All the miſerie in the
<pb facs="tcp:9886:21"/>worlde, was incloſed within this wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed prieſt, for he had alwaies a great old coffer, wherin he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually locked with a keye whith did hang at the point of his reate, all the breade that came from the Churche at offeringes, forgetting at no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſame vnlorked, beeing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and buttrie. For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all the houſe a man might diſcerne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that coulde bee eaten; neyther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in the chimney, nor Cheeſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> vpon ſheltice, nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>! &amp; broken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> corner as common<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y in other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> which things ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſeen &amp; not taſted, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> me much: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, was a rope of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and vnder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> foure dayes. And when I ſhew &amp; come for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ye to talke my due, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> were am ſtraunger <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his hand in a his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp; with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, woulde ſay, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> immediatly de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iue, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mee againe, their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> nothing but crainuie vp meate. So that he that had
<pb facs="tcp:9886:21"/>heard him, would haue iudged there had bene vnder the coſtodie of that key, al the confectures of <hi>Valentia.</hi> But for any thing that was there, beſide the rope of Onion y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hong on a natle, the deuill him ſelfe might haue had parte, and of them hee kept ſuch ſtraight accounte,
<note place="margin">A blanke the xii. part of an Engliſh pen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. The cuſtome is there vpon Saturday to eate the heads, the fecte and bowels of all beaſtes with his licence.</note> that if I hadde taken at any time more then my ordinarie, I ſhould dearely haue bought it. After that I had continued a while with him. I was ready <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ury houre to fal downe dead for hunger. His vſe was, to dine &amp; ſup with as muche fleſh as moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the value offlue blankes, wherof I was ſure neuer to taſte<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vnleſſe it were of the broth, which ſometimes hee would friendly parte betweene vs, and ſo for bread, I would to god I might haue ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> halfe as muche as was ſufficiente. Vpon Saterdayes, as the cuſtome was in that citie, he would ſend me for a ſhéepes head that ſhould coſt three Mareuedies,
<note place="margin">Two blankes a Mareuedi.</note> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of when it was ſod, hee woulde eate both the eyes, the tongue, and the braine yea, and al the fleſh on both the chèeke bones: Then reaching mee the platter, with a fewe naked bones, would ſay, take down
<pb facs="tcp:9886:22"/>this to thée, and reioyce, ſeeing that thou haſt the world at wil, I am ſure the Pope him ſelfe hathe nowe no better life than thou haſt: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would I anſwer him, with lowe voyce. God ſende thée alwayes the like. I had not dwelte with him thrée weekes, but I was ſo leane y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my legges were ſcarce able to beare me: the hunger was ſo greate which I ſuſtained, that I neuer thought to eſcape death, vnleſſe that Gods helpe and mine owne indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie wold finde ſome remedy to ſaue my life. And for to vſe my accuſtomed ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tie, there was not wherewithal, ſéeing that there was nothing there to giue aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault vnto: yea although there had bene, I might neuer haue bene able to deceiue him, as I had done the poore blinde man, vppon whome I pray God take mercy if hee bee dead with his laſt blowe. For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> beit he was craftie, yet wanting his precious ſight, I was ſure bee could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſee what I hourely did. But there was neuer man that hadde quicker eye-ſight than this Prleſt: For at offering time, the ſiluer was not ſo ſoone falne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the baſen, but that ſtreight hée had it
<pb facs="tcp:9886:22"/>regiſtred, hauing alwayes one eye to my hand, &amp; an other to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people: and his eyes woulde ſo roll in his head, as if they had béene of quickeſiluer. As ſoone as offring was done he would take the baſen out of my hands, and lay it vpon the aulter, ſo that I was neuer able to deceiue him of one blanks. And whiles I continued with him, (or to ſay better,) whiles that I conſumed my ſelfe in this miſerable ſeruice, he neuer ſent me to the tauerne, for as much as the value of a blanke in wine, but that ſmall quantitie which hée had offred on the Sunday, hée kepte al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in his coffer ſo ſparingly, that it would laſt him al the wéek ouer. And for to hide his couetouſneſſe, he would ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſay vnto mée, my boy, all Prieſtes ought to be ſober in eating and drinking &amp; therfore I dare not break order as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other do, Now you ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſée how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer lied falſly therein,
<note place="margin">A Saluter is a kinde of drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prophets in Spaine which take vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the healing of mad dogges,</note> for at burials &amp; dir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, where hée had meate at other mens charges, he would eate like a wolfe, more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> foure me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; drinke as it were a Salu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: and becauſe his office was always to ſay dirge, at ſuch times (god forgiue me)
<pb facs="tcp:9886:23"/>was alwayes an enemy to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and onely, becauſe that then wee ſhoulde fare well, and haue meate at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, I wiſhed and prayed God that he woulde euerie day call vp one to heauen. When wee went to miniſter the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſuch as were ſicke, my maiſter woulde deſire thoſe that were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, to pray for the ſicke man,
<note place="margin">Lazaro had not eared though the king had died, ſo that hee might haue had meare to ſtay his hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſurely I was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer one of the laſt that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vnſtring God with al my hart, not that he would doe to the patient according is his will, (as other prayed) but that he would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch him out of the world: and when a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of them eſcaped death, I was ready (God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> me) to wiſh him at the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, and who ſo euer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſure to haue of me many bleſſings, and prayers for his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> I dwelt with this maiſter about ſir moneths, and in that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> died only vnperſons, which I certainly ſlew to at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> leaſt, the earneſt requeſt of my pray <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was cauſe of their death: for God the father perceiuing the raging hunger which I continually ſuſtained, reioyſed (as I thinke) to ſtay them, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> my life thereby, conſidering that
<pb facs="tcp:9886:23"/>otherwiſe my diſeaſe coulde not be reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> I was neuer aceaſe, but when we had<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> burials: The day that there was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, my teeth ſhould haue no work my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> would faint, becauſe that I had beene vſed ſometimes to haue my bet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> filled. At ſuche times I ſounds caſe in nothing but in death, which then I wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, as well for my ſelfe, as I had done before for the ſicke men. I determined oftentimes to departe from that miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable maſter, yet fearing ſo to do, for two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe I durſte not truſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my legs, which by hunger were brought to great weakeneſſe, ſecondly, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with my ſelfe, ſaying, I haue had two maſters, with the firſt I died for hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, whom when I had forſaken I cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed vpon this other, which with the very ſame diſeaſe hath almoſt brought mee to my graue: therfore I made account that if I ſhould forſake the ſecond &amp; meet with a thirde that were worſe then theſe two, then there were no remedie but plaine death. Wherefore I neuer durſt depart from him, beeing aſſured to finde all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates worſe and worſe, knowing that to
<pb facs="tcp:9886:24"/>deſcend an other degrée, <hi>Lazaro</hi> ſhould be ſoon forgotten, being once rid out of this world.
<note place="margin">Lazaro was a good Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beleeuing that all goodneſſe came fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God.</note> And being in ſuch afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (God of his grace deliuer euery faithfull Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian from the like) not knowing how to cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell my ſelfe, my miſery dayly increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, vpon a day, when by chaunce my wretched maſter had gone abroad, there ariued by cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dore a tinker, which I beléeue was an Angel diſguiſed, ſente from God, who demaunded for worke: I anſwered ſoftly, thou haſte inough to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in me, and I beléene more than thou canſt doe. But as it was no time then to delay the matter, (by diuine inſpiration) I ſaide vnto him, vncle, I haue loſte the key of this coffer, I feare y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my maiſter wil beate mee, for gods ſake looke amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt your keyes if there be any that will open it, I wil conſider your paines: the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tinker began to aſſay, nowe one key, now another, of this great bunch, and I helped him with my prayers, ſo that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly before I was aware, he opened it: whereof I was ſo gladde, that mée thought I did ſée in figure, (as they ſay) the face of God, when I beheld the bread
<pb facs="tcp:9886:24"/>within it: and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had done all, I ſaid vnto him, I haue no money, but take this for thy paiment, ſo he tooke one of the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt loues, and after he had deliuered mée the key, hee departed right well pleaſed, and I as well content as he. At that time I touched nothing, partly becauſe I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued my ſelfe to bee the Lorde of ſuche treaſure, that by reaſon of that keye hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger durſt neuer againe approch me. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continently after, who commeth in, but my vnhappy maſter, and as God would, he neuer tooke heed of the loafe, which the heauenly tinker had borrowed. The next day after, as ſoone as he went abroade, I began to open my paradiſe of bread, and what betweene my hands and my teeth, with the twinkling of an eye I made a loafe inuiſible, forgetting in no wiſe to lock the cheſt againe: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I began cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to ſwéepe the houſe, iudging y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> by ſuch remedy I might eaſe my ſorowfull life. So I paſſed that day and the nexte, with much mirth. But my contrary Fortune wente aboute to hinder mee to enioye ſuche pleaſure long, for the thyrd days iuſte, a tercian ague came
<pb facs="tcp:9886:25"/>vppon mée, in perceiuing him that had ſlayne mée with hunger, at an vndue houre, ouer the cheſt, tuching &amp; toſſing, accounting and reckoning his breade. I diſſembled the matter, as I had not perceiued him, and in my ſecret prayer and deuotion, I prayed: ſaint Iohn to blinde him. And after that he had bene a good while caſting his acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>umpte vppon his fingers, he ſaid vnto me, if it were not that this coffer is ſo ſure, I would ſay that ſome of my bread hath bene taken away, but from hencefoorth I will kéepe good accounte of it, there is nowe left nyne loues beſides a broken piece: then ſaid I with lowe voyce, nine euils God ſende vnto thee, It ſeemed vnto mee with that which hée had ſaid, my hart to be pierced through with an arrowe, and my ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke began to riue for hunger, percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing how I was put to my former diet. He then departed out, and I opened the ſaide coffer to comforte my ſelfe a little, and beholding the bread, which I durſts not touch, but worſhipping it, I behelde &amp; counted it ouer, to ſee if the wretch had ouerreckoned him ſelfe: but I founde his
<pb facs="tcp:9886:25"/>account more iuſte, that I woulde haue wiſhed it by the one halfe: the moſt that I could doe, was to giue it a thouſand kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and to cut a little delicately of that place where it was cut before: and with that I paſſed ouer that day, yet not ſo me rily as I did the other. But now becauſe two or thrée dayes before I had breade at will, the appetite in my ſtomacke did increaſe in ſuch ſorte, that I was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt dead for hunger: wherefore being alone, I did nothing but open and locks againe the coffer, beholding alwayes that bread as a God. And God himſelf which ſuccoureth thoſe that are afflicted, ſeeing me in ſuch neceſſitie, brought a little remedie vnto my memorie, which was, that I remembred with my ſelfe this coffer to be olde and broken in many places, and although the holes were lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, yet might it bee thoughte that Mice had entred therein to damage th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> breade. And to take out a whole loafe, the wretch wold ſone eſpie the fault yet this may be better born withal: ſo the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to claw the breade with my nailes, vpon a ſimple napkin that was there, taking
<pb facs="tcp:9886:26"/>one loafe and leauing another, ſo that of euerie third or fourth, I would be ſure to take ſome cru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes, &amp; euen as if they were confects I did ſwalow the ſame, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte my ſtomacke. When hee ſhoulde come to dinner, opening his cheſte, and eſpying incontinently the hurte, he did iudge that rats had done that ſpoile, for I had ſo counterfeited their gnawing, that any man would haue thought the ſame: wherefore hee ſought all corners of the cheſt, and at the laſte hée eſpied certaine holes where hee ſuſpected they had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred: whereupon he called me in all haſte, ſaying, <hi>Lazaro,</hi> ſee here what perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath beene done this night vpon our breade. I began to maruell, demaunding what it ſhould be? what ſhould it be ſaid he but rats, which leaue nothing wholed we we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t then to dinner, &amp; as God wold I had vetter allowance then I was wont, for with his knife he pared away all that which hee thought the mice had touched, ſaying, take eate this my boy, Mice are cleane. I chanced y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day to fare better, for he augme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted my allowa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which I had made, by the trauel of my handes,
<pb facs="tcp:9886:26"/>or to ſay truthe, of my nailes. We ended our dinner for al that, ſomewhat to ſone, yet there came another plunge vpon me, perceiuing howe the Prieſt was earneſt in pulling nailes out of the wall, and ſeeking little bourdes to ſlop the holes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: wherfore I ſaid to my ſelfe (Lord God) vnto howe many perils and cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of Fortune are humaine crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſubiect? how ſhort a time doe the pleaſures of our troubleſome life laſt? lo where I am nowe, whiche truſted by this my poore remedie, to eaſe my mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie, being in beſte hope of good aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, my euill lucke would not conſent, but opened the ſighte of my couetous maiſters vnderſtanding, cauſing him to haue more ſubtile wit than he had giuen him by nature, although ſuch wretches are commonly ſubtile enough. When he had dummed vp the holes, I thought his cheſt ſhoulde bee ſhutte to my comforte, and opened to my paine, and therefore I neuer left lamenting, vntill that the curious Carpenter with his companie of bourds had ended his worke of nayling, and when he had done, ſaid: now ye trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torly
<pb facs="tcp:9886:27"/>Mice you muſt change purpoſe, for there is no more profite for you in this houſe. As ſoone as euer hée went abrode, I went to view his worke, and I percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that he had not left in his olde cheſte one hole vnſtopped, not ſo much as a place for a flie to get in: notwithſtanding without hope of gaine I opened the cheſt with my vnprofitable key, and there vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited two loaues begon, which hee had thoughte the Mice has carued, and from them once againe I ſcraped a little quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie, touching the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lightly like a nimble maiſter of defence, for neceſſitie at that time my miſtreſſe, cauſed mee days and night to imagine howe I might liue and ſeeke remedie for my ſore, whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hunger taught me the way, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly maketh men haue ready wittes. I beganne then to ſtudie aboute my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, ſéeking meanes to drawe ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie out of the ſaide couetous coffer: perceiuing one nighte that my maiſter ſlept ſoundly (or at leaſt made me beleeue ſo) by his ſnorting &amp; blowing, I roſe on my feete, and as I had taken order with my ſelfe the daye before what ſhoulde bée
<pb facs="tcp:9886:27"/>done that night, I had left an olde knife which was caſte aboute the houſe, in a place where it might be founde at need, &amp; went to that happie coffer: and where it ſeemed to haue leaſt defence, I gaue the aſſault with my ruſtie knife, which ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued my tourne wel for a wimble: but the cheſt by reaſon of good yéeres, beeing weake, without ſtrength, very ſofte and tender, did ſtraight wayes render &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent that I ſhould make for my commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie a good hole in the ſide of it, and that done, opening the wounded cheſt, and knowing euerye loafe ſeuerally by the touch, I did as I had done before, and by that meanes beeing ſomewhat comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, hauing locked the cheſt againe. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to my pallet, wherupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſlept lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle (&amp; as I thinke) mine euill ſupper was cauſe of that, for otherwiſe, at that time of the night the king of France his cares could neuer breake me of my ſleepe. On the morning the Prieſt my maſter per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing the hurte which was done as well to the breade as to the coffer, began to curſe the Mice, ſaying, what meaneth this? there was neuer Mouſe wont to go
<pb facs="tcp:9886:28"/>here before now-and certainly his words were true, for if any houſe in the whole kingdome might be priuileged fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Mice it might be his, for Mice are neuer wont to dwell where no parings of meate doe fall. But nowe he began againe to ſeeke nailes about the ways, and little bourds, to make defence againſt the traitorous Mice: but as ſoone as night came that he went to his reſt. I roſe vp with my tooles, and loked what he ſtopped in the day time, I broke vp againe in the night: finally, the one and the other of vs tooke ſuch paine, that this prouerbe was fulfild, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one doore is ſhut the other openeth: at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt, wee ſeemed to haue <hi>Penelopes</hi> wcb in hande, what ſo euer hee wrought in the day, I vndid again in the night, in ſo much y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we brought the poore coffer to ſuch eſtate, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> who ſo euer wold properly talke of it, might compare it to an olde boate or briga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tin, for that number of olde nayles that was driuen into eche ſide of it, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaw his remedy preuailed not he ſaide, this coffer is ſo olde &amp; ſo weake, that it is no longer able to defende oure vittalles from vermine, it is nowe at
<pb facs="tcp:9886:28"/>that point y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if I meddle any more with it, them ore it will decay, and ſo at length be able to do vs no ſeruice at all, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture euill fortune will cauſe mee ſpende two or thrée ſhillinges to buy an other: the beſt remedie that I can finde, ſeing this doth not preuaile, is to ſet vp a trappe within it, to take theſe cruell rats: wherupon he went in mediatly and borowed one of his neighbours, which he had continually bent within the coffer, with a baite of cheeſe paring, which was laide onely for my comforte and eaſe, for although I coulde well haue eaten my bread alone, without y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> help of any thing elſe, to cauſe my appetite, yet the cheeſe paring which I woulde pull out of the trappe, gaue me trimme taſte with my mouſe eaten bread. But when he ſhould perceiue the bread ſo ſpoyled with ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, and the cheeſe eaten, and the rat that did the deede not taken, then woulde he wiſh the trap at the deuill, demaunding of his neighbours what it might bée, that the cheeſe ſhoulde be eaten, and the Rat not taken, yea and the trap fallen? the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours would anſwere that it was no rat
<pb facs="tcp:9886:29"/>that did that harme,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>akes are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot there to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ort much in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> for foode.</note> for at one time or other ſhe had beene taken. And amongſt the reſt one ſaide, I doe remember that a ſnake was wonte to haunts your houſe, and by all reaſon it is ſhée that hath done the deede, for ſhee beeing long, mighte eaſily eate the cheeſe, and although the trap did fall, yet becauſe hir bodye entred not in all, ſhe might well and eaſely get out and ſcape. This neighbours ſaying did ſatiſfie the whole com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anie, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially my maiſter, which from that time forwarde neuer ſlept one night ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for when he had hearde the leaſt noiſe amongeſt the wood, hée woulde thinke that it were the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ke gnawing the coffer, wherefore he would ſtreight be vp with a cudgell, which fithence he entr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d into ſuch ſuſpectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, was always ready at his beds head, wher with he would beate the poore coffer ſo hard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, to feare the ſnake, that hee waken all the neghbours with the noyſe. And as for mee, I neuer ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pt, for often times in the night he wold turne me and my pallet ouer and ouer, thinking that the ſnake had gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er into my bed or into my apparell, for hee
<pb facs="tcp:9886:29"/>was informed, that thoſe beaſtes often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſeking heate, haue come into chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens Cradles, &amp; b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tten them to death. I wold always make as though I ſlept: then hee would in the morning ſay vnto mee <hi>O Lazaro,</hi> haſt thou heard no noyſe this night. I did purſue the Snak, and I was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>afraid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> had gotten into thy bed, for they are colde, &amp; therefore ſeke heate. Then anſwered I, I pray God ſhe hath not bitten me. I feare Snakes as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil. He continued in ſuch fearefull fama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte, that he neuer ſlepte, ſo that &amp; bering the Snake, du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt neuer approche the cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, but onely in the day time, whiles hee was at Churche, or abroade in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> towne, then woulde I make my aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault: whereof when he had knowledge, perceiuing that he was not able to finde any further remedie, would euery night (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s I haue told you) be raging mad. All that I feared then was, that he with his diligence w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ulde meete with my priuie key which I had hidde vnder the bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrawe: But for more ſuretie, at night tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I woulde a waves keepe it in my mouth, for when that I dwelt with the
<pb facs="tcp:9886:30"/>blynd man, I had brought my mouth to ſuch vſe by conueying money into it, that it ſerued me ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for a purpoſe. I can wel remember, when ſometimes I haue had in it .xiitj. or xv. deniers, and not hindred my eating, otherwiſe I had neuer beens maiſter of denier, but that the curſſed blinde man woulde haue founde it out, not leauing one ſeame or wrinckle of my coate vnſought. Therefore as I tel you, I did euery nighte put the keye in my mouth for a ſafegarde, &amp; by that meanes I ſlepte ſoundly, not fearing that he ſhoulde finde it. Notwithſtanding, when that the euill houre could not be eſcaped, my diligence was all but vaine: it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed my fatall deſtenie (or to ſay truth) my ſinnes, that vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a night when I was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleepe, the keye happened ſo to tourne in my mouth, being wide open, in ſuch ſort, that my breath comming foorth through the hole of the keye, which was hollowe, made ſuch loude whiſtling (as euill for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune woulde) that my carefull maiſter hearde it, who thought certainely that it had bene the hiſſing of the Snake, (as ſurely it might be like) hée roſe vp very
<pb facs="tcp:9886:30"/>ſoftly holding his cudgell faſt, and by the noyſe of the hiſſing came by little and litle ſtreight to me, without making any noyſe, to the intent the Snake ſhould not heare him. When hee was neers me, hee thought certainely that the Snake was there in the ſtrawe, wherfore he lifted vp his cudgell to kill her, and with all his ſtrength hée diſcharged vppon my heade ſuch a cruell blowe, that he wounded me to death. Whereupon, he knowing that he had ſtricken me, belike by the groning that I made after the receit of the blow, ſuſpecting what had hapned, cried out to awake me, but as ſoone as he touched me with his handes, hee felte abundance of bloud iſſue out of my heade: wherefore conſidering what hurt he had done mee, hee wente in haſte for a candle, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourning with it in his hande, found me groning &amp; gaſping with my keye in my mouth, which I neuer let goe, beeing halfe out, euen as it was when it made ſuche hiſſing, whereat the killer of Snakes maruelled, eſpecially when hée behelde the keye, which hée tooke out of my mouth, and vewing it, hee percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="tcp:9886:31"/>what it was, for in workemanſhip it differeth nothing from his. But for more ſuretie hee wente ſtreighte to proue it, and ſo then eſpied the whole diſceit. God knoweth then howe hée bragged, that hée had taken the Rat and the Snake that had made him ſuch warre, and that ſo deſtroyed his breade: what happened the three dayes following, I am not able to tel, for I was as it were in a whales bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie (but only this that I haue tolde you: which I had heard my maſter report, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that I was retourned to my ſelfe, for hee declared the whole matter to as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as came in and out. The third day af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to recouer, maruelling much, when I perceiued my ſelfe beeing in my ſtrawe, my head full of plaiſters, oyles, and oyntments, and being thereat ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, I ſaid what meneth this? The prieſt then anſwered, the meaning of this is, that I had chaſed away the Ratte and the Snake that haue done me ſuch hurt: then calling to minde my affaires, I ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected my hurte, and the cauſe thereof: then came there in an olde woman, with certaine of the neighbours, to vndo the
<pb facs="tcp:9886:31"/>cloutes about my head, and to dreſſe my woundes, and being glad to ſee mee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered, ſaide, there is no danger, now in him, ſeeing that he hath his ſenſes, they began then to recite my afflictions, they laughing and I weeping. After all this, they gaue me meate, I being almoſt dead for hunger. Much a do they had to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer mee, but by little and little I wared ſtrong, &amp; at .xv. dayes ende, I roſe vp and was out of daunger, yet not without hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, howebeit halfe healed. The next day after that I roſe, my maſter tooke me by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hande, and brought me out at the dore, and leauing me in the ſtreate, ſaide vnto me: <hi>Lazaro,</hi> from this day foorth, thou ſhalt be at thine owne libertie, and not vnder my ſubiection, the Lorde bée with thee: go ſéek thée a maſter, I haue no néed of ſuch a diligent ſernaunt, it is not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, but that thou haſt bene ſeruaunt to ſome blinde man. And therewith bleſſing him ſelfe from me, as though I had beene poſſeſſed with ſome euill ſpirite, hee ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth him in and locketh faſt his doore.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:9886:32"/>
            <head>How Lazaro placeth him ſelfe to ſerue a Squire, and what happened to him in his ſeruice.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y this meanes I was forced to helpe my ſelfe beeing weake, &amp; ſhortly after, I came by helpe of good people, to this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble citie of <hi>Toledo,</hi> where (I thanke God) my wound cloſed vp. As long as I was ſicke, euery man gaue me his charitie, but after that I was once whole, euery man would ſay, thou vaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bond and leiterer, why doſt thou not ſéek a maſter? Then I murmuring with my ſelfe, wold ſay, &amp; where the deuill ſhall I finde him, vnleſſe God, as hee made the world, make me one. But now Ideman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding almes from dore to dore for Gods ſake, I found little remedy, for charitie had then aſcended vp to heauen. At the laſt God cauſed me to méet with a ſquire which walked thorow the ſtreate, in very ſumptuous apparel, &amp; cleanly, his pace in going wel meaſured after good order. He
<pb facs="tcp:9886:32"/>behelde me and I him, and he ſaide vnto me: boy, doeſt thou want a matter? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, I woulde faine haue a good ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſir. Then followe mee ſaid he: God hath ſent thee good fortune to meete with me, thou haſt prayed well this daye, I thanke God, for that which I had heard him ſay, and for that he ſeemed by his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour and countenances to bee euen hee, that I had ſo much longed for. I met with this thirde maiſter betime in the morning, and hee led mee after him tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the moſt parte of the citie: we paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed through the market place, where ther was ſold bread, and other prouiſion:
<note place="margin">Gentlemen vſe to buy their meate in the market them ſelues.</note> I looked when he would haue lode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me there with meate, for it was then, that euery man prouided and bought things neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie for their dinner. But with comely and large pace hee went by, and lefte that place behind him: then I ſaid to my ſelfe,
<note place="margin">There is not ſuch prouiſion of meate in Spaine as there is in England.</note> peraduenture hes doeth not ſee here that which doeth contente him, hee will buy in an other place: we walked ſo long that the clocke ſtrok eleuen, then went hee to the chiefe Churche, and I after him, where I ſawe him moſt deuoutly heare
<pb facs="tcp:9886:33"/>ſeruice, when all was ended, &amp; the people departed, he came ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Churche and marched loyſurely do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ne a ſtreate:
<note place="margin">He we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſo l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t to the Church to came that his dinner might be made ready.</note> and as for me, I went ioyfully, the beſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in the worlde, perceiuing howe that we did not ſtay to ſeeke our dinner, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining that this my newe maiſter had bene ſome great perſonage, and that hee had his houſe pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uided before hande, that we ſhould finde dinner ready, yea ſuch as I deſired, and as I had neede of. At that tune the clocke ſtroke one after noone, when wee arriued at a houſe before the which my maſter had ſtayd I with him, then hee throwing his cloake ouer his leaf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſhoulder very ciuilly, drewe out a key out of his ſleue to open his doore, we then entred in, the entrance wherof was ſo darke and vnhandſome, that it might feare any man liuing to enter in, how be it, there was within it a prety litle count and reaſonable chambers: and when we were within, hee putteth off his cloake, demaunding mée whether my handes were cleane, we ſhooke it, and then dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled it handſomely, and after he had blo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen cleanly the duſt away from an olde
<pb facs="tcp:9886:33"/>benche that was there, he layde it vp: that beeing done, he ſat him downe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding of mee at large what countrey man I was, &amp; howe I came to the citie: I gaue him a larger account than I was willing: for I thought it a more conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient time to commaunde mee to lay the cloath, and to take out pottage, than to make ſuch inquiraunce: yet for all that, bringing foorth the beſte lyes I coulde frame for my ſelfe, I made him account what I was, reckening all the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that was in my perſonage, leauing apart all that which I thought was not to be rehearſed in that place: when I had declared all he ſtaied a while, and by that time I did ſee an euill ſlgne: for it was almoſte two a clocke, and yet he was no readier to dine tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he that had bene dead. I maruelled moreouer, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I perceiued that hee had locked his dore with his key, &amp; that I could not heare any liuing crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſtur, neither aboue, nor beneath: all that euer I did ſee was the naked walls,
<note place="margin">As the Prieſt had.</note> not ſo muche, as a chayre or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oole, nor a table, nor yet a coffer, as the other man had: finally you would haue ſaide, it had
<pb facs="tcp:9886:34"/>bene a houſe, not inhabited. A whyle af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he demanded mee whether I had dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, I anſwered ſaying, no ſir, for it was not eight a clocke when I met with your maſterſhip this morning, (then ſaide he) as early as it was, I had broken my faſt, and whenſoeuer I breake my faſt in the morning, I neuer eate againe vntill it bée night, therefore paſſe thou ouer the time as well as thou canſt, and wee will make amendes at ſupper: your worſhip may well thinke that when I heard theſe wordes I was ready to fall downe dead, not ſo muche for hunger, as for playnely perceiuing, that then fortune was alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether mine ennemie. Then began my ſorrowes to appeare vnto me againe, and I to lament my miſfortune: then came there to my minde, the conſideration that I made when I was aboute to departe from the Prieſt,
<note place="margin">Poore Lazero did beare his maſters dinner and his owne in his boſon e for feare of leeſing it.</note> weyghing with my ſelfe, that although hée was moſt wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and miſerable, yet peraduenture I might meete with a worſſe: finally, I lamented and wept my troubleſome life that was paſte, and my death that did approch: and yet for all this I diſſembled
<pb facs="tcp:9886:34"/>the matter as well as I coulde, and ſaide vnto him, ſir I thanke God, I am a boy that doth not greatly care for eating and drinking, for I may well compare with any of my age for ſobernes and meaſure in eating, and ſo haue I béene alwayes eſtéemed of as many maiſters as I haue ſerued: bee then aunſwered ſaying, it is a vertue to liue ſoberly, therefore I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend thée much: Pogs fill them ſelues, and wyſo men eate diſcréetely what is onely ſufficient for them. I nowe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande you well ſir, ſayde I to my ſelfe, euill lucke light vppon ſuche vertue and goodneſſe as theſe my maiſters doe finde in hunger: immediatly after all this, I conueyed my ſelfe behind the dore, where I drewe certaine péeces of breade out of my boſome, which were left of that I hadde receiued for Gods ſake two dayes before. But hée perceiuing mée, ſayde, come hither boy, what doeſt thou eate? I came vnto him, and did ſhewe thr bread, whereof hée tooke a peece, whiche of two or thrée was the beſte and the biggeſt, ſaying, by my ſoule me thinks this bread is good and ſauarouſe: yea mary ſy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, at
<pb facs="tcp:9886:35"/>this time eſpecially, ſayde: I. Is ſo in deed ſaid he, but where hadſt thou it, was it moulded with cleane handes? that I know not ſaid I, howbeit I find it good. I pray God it bee cleane, ſaide the poore Gentleman: and with that putting his hande to his mouth, deuoured quickly all that I had giuen him: and ſomewhat before we had ended, he ſaid, by God this bread hath a good taſte, howe ſauerous it is. And as for me then, I perceiued vpon which foote he halted, I made haſt to eat, perceiuing him to be ſo diſpoſed, that if he had made an ende before mee, I thought he wold gently haue offred to helpe mee: therefore wee ended both at one time in good order. He began then with his hand to bruſhe away a fewe crummes, which had faine vpon his breaſt,
<note place="margin">In Spaine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, drinke no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſome that may haue wine; but this ſquare dranke it for want of better.</note> &amp; after that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into a chamber that was there, and thence broughte foorth an olde potte bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken mouthed, &amp; dranke wel, &amp; then he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered me the potte. But I to ſeeme ſober and modeſt, ſaid ſir I drinke no wine: it is water, ſaid he, thou maiſt well drinke of it: then I tooke the potte, but I dranke not much, for it was not thruſt, but hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb facs="tcp:9886:35"/>that troubled me. We paſſed the time ſo vntill that it was nighte, reaſoning of ſundry matters which he demaunded of me, whercunto I anſwered as well as I could. Then we entred into the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber from whence hee had brought foorthe his drinking potte, hee ſaying: boy, go to the other ſide, and marke howe we make this bed, that thou maiſt knowe howe to make it from hencefoorth. I went to the one ſide and he to the other, and made the poore bed, which was an eaſie matter to doe, for it was thus as I will tell you: A ſheepes hurdell layde ouerhwarte two trefles, a ſilly rotten harde matreſſe, and vppon that his bed clothes, which by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſeldome waſhing coulde not be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerned in colour from the matreſſe, the which had not halfe ſo much wool as néed required: wée turned it to make it ſofte, but that was vnpoſſible to doe, for ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e harde it is for a man to make a harde thing ſofte, and the diuell a thing was within the cruell mattreſſe at all, for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was ſpreade vppon the hurdle of big<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſtickes, euery ſticke appeared thorow, en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as like as could be, to the ribs of a carian
<pb facs="tcp:9886:36"/>this time eſpecially, ſayde: I. Is ſo in deed ſaid he, but where hadſt thou it, was it moulded with cleane handes? that I know not ſaid I, howbeit I find it good. I pray God it bee cleane, ſaide the poore Gentleman: and with that putting his hande to his mouth, deuoured quickly all that I had giuen him: and ſomewhat before we had ended, he ſaid, by God this bread hath a good taſte, howe ſauerous it is. And as for me then, I perceiued vpon which foote he halted, I made haſt to eat, perceiuing him to be ſo diſpoſed, that if he had made an ende before mee, I thought he wold gently haue offred to helpe mee: therefore wee ended both at one time in good order. He began then with his hand to bruſhe away a fewe crummes, which had faine vpon his breaſt,
<note place="margin">In Spaine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, drinke no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſome that may haue wine; but this ſqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e drankeſt for want of better.</note> &amp; after that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into a chamber that was there, and thence broughte foorth an olde potte bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken mouthed, &amp; dranke wel, &amp; then be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered me the potte. But I to ſeeme ſober and modeſt, ſaid ſir I drinke no wine: it is water, ſaid he, thou maiſt well drinke of it: then I tooke the porte, but I dranke not much, for it was not thruſt, but hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb facs="tcp:9886:36"/>that troubled me. We paſſed the time ſo vntill that it was nighte, reaſoning of ſundry matters which he demaunded of me, whercunto I anſwered as well as I could. Then we entred into the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber from whence hee had brought foorthe his drinking potte, hee ſaying: boy, go to the other ſide, and marke howe we make this bed, that thou maiſt knowe howe to make it from hencefoorth. I went to the one ſide and he to the other, and made the poore bed, which was an eaſie matter to doe, for it was thus as I will tell you: A ſhéepes hurdell layde ouerhwarte two treſles, a ſilly rotten harde matreſſe, and vppon that his bed clothes, which by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſeldome waſhing coulde not be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerned in colour from the matreſſe, the which had not halfe ſo much wool as néed required: wée turned it to make it ſofte, but that was vnpoſſible to doe, for verſe harde it is for a man to make a harde thing ſofte, and the diuell a thing was within the cruell mattreſſe at all, for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was ſpreade vppon the hurdle of biggs ſtickes, euery ſticke appeared thorow, en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as like as could be, to the ribs of a carian
<pb facs="tcp:9886:37"/>leane Hogge, wée ſpred vpon the hungry miſerable matris, a couerlet ſuteable to the reſte of the ſtuffe, what ſtuffe it was off. I can not well deuiſe: before that we hadde made the beddes it was night, and he ſaid: <hi>Lazaro,</hi> it is nowe late, and from hence to the market place where proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of meate is ſolde, it is a long waye,
<note place="margin">The ſtreetes are natrowe &amp; darke few lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes are ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g out.</note> and beſides that ruffians and théeues doe méete men euery night to ſpoyle them of their cloakes &amp; caps in the darke, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs paſſe ouer this night as well as we may, to morowe God will prouide better for vs. I am not prouided of meate becauſe I haue bene hetherto alone with out a ſeruaunt, and I haue alwayes ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken my meales in the Citie, but from hencefoorth wée will kéepe a newe order: ſir ſaid I, take no care for me, I can paſſe ouer one night, &amp; more if néede bee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out meate, &amp; that will bee cauſe that thou ſhalt liue longer ſaid he, for as wiſe men affirme, there is nothing that can make a mancliue longer than to eate a little. If that be true ſaid I to my ſelfe. I ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>for I haue always bene conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to keepe that rule, and I thinke I
<pb facs="tcp:9886:37"/>am fortuned to obſerue it as long as I liue. After all this hee went to bed, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his hoſe and his dubled his bolſter, and cauſing me to lye at his féete, where I neuer ſlept winke, for the hard hurdle neuer lefte galling my naked bones, which by hunger and ſorrowe together, had not leſt on them nor yet on all my body beſides, and ounce of fleſh:
<note place="margin">Hunger is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to ſleepe.</note> and as I chaunced to eate nothing that daye, my braine was ſo light, that I could neuer take reſt. Wherefore (God forgiue mee) I curſed my ſelfe and my fortune a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times, and that which was worſe than all this, I neuer durſt change ſides for feare of waking him: wherefore I deſired death. The next morning when he roſe, hée began to ſhake and to make cleane his hoſe, his dublet, &amp; his cloake, I was his bruſhe, ſo he araide himſelfe at leiſure: I gaue him then water for his hands, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had occupied his combe, he taketh his ſword &amp; kiſſeth the pommel, and as hee was putting it to his girdle, ſaide vnto mée: My boy, if thou kneweſt what a blade this is, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wouldeſt maruel, there is no gold that can buy it of me, for
<pb facs="tcp:9886:38"/>of as many as <hi>Antonio</hi> made, he coulde neuer giue ſuch temper to any as he gaue this: then drawing it out of the ſcabbarde he taſted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> edge with his fingers, ſaying, ſceſt thou it? I dare vndertake to cut a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder with it a whole fleece of wooll: I anſwered him ſoftely to my ſelfe, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and I with my teeth though they be not of ſuch harde mettall a loafe of bread weighing iiu. pound. Then vp went the ſword againe, hanging it at his girdle. and after all this he marched out into the ſtreate, with a leaſurely well meaſured pace, holding his bodye ſtraight, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king therewith and with his head a very good countenaunce, caſting the ende of his cloake ſometimes vpon his ſhoulder, &amp; otherwhyles vnder his arme, with his right hand alwayes on his ſide, and as he was going forth ſaid, <hi>Lazaro,</hi> looke well about the houſe, while I do go and heare ſeruice, make the bedde, and then fetche ſome water here at the riuer beneath, looke thedoore leaſt any body rob vs, and lay the keye vnderneath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> threſhold, that I may come in: hée went vp the ſtreate with ſuch comely geſture &amp; countenance,
<pb facs="tcp:9886:38"/>that he that had not knowen him, would haue iudged him to haue bene nere kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man vnto the high Conſtable of Spaine. or at the leaſt his chiefe Chamberlein. I remained then alone, ſaying to my ſelfe, bleſſed art thou O God which ſendeſt the ſickneſſe &amp; giueſt the remedy, who would thinke that ſhould meete my Lord &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, with ſuch geſture &amp; cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, but that hée had ſupped well yeſternight, yea and that he had ſlept in a good bed? and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be now early, who wold thinke but that he had broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his faſt wel? Great are thy ſecret doings O lord, &amp; all people are ignorant of them: might not his good diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, his reaſonable cloke and coate deceiue any man? who woulde diſtruſte that ſuch a noble Gentleman had eaten nothing all yeſterday, but one piece of bread which his ſeruant <hi>Lazaro</hi> had kept in the cheſt of his boſom a day &amp; a night, ſo that it could not be (to ſay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth) very cleane? who woulde ſuſpect that hee had dried this morning his face and his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds vpon the ſkirts of his coate for want of a towell? I am certain no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would iudge it in him, O Lorde howe many are there
<pb facs="tcp:9886:39"/>in the worlde, that are in ſuch brauery as this my maſter is in, which doe ſuffer more for a little vaine glories ſake, than they would do for the loue of thée. I ſtoode in the doore ſo long remembring all thoſe things, that my maiſter paſſed thorow a long and narrow ſtreete, then I went in, and within a minute of an houre, I viſited the whole houſe aboue and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neat, without ſtaying, or finding wherat to ſtay. When I had made the vnlucky b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dde, I tooke my pot and went ſtreighte to the Riuer, and being ready to take vp my water, I might perceiue my maiſter in a Garden ouer the water, in greate talke with two comely women, whiche by their countenaunce ſeemed to be ſome of them, wherof in <hi>Toledo</hi> a number are rifely found: &amp; many of them take an vſe of going abroade early in the morning in Sommer time, to take the ayre in thoſe Gardens, and to breake their faſte with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prouiſion of their owne vnder trees and ſhadowes, nere that pleaſant Riuer, truſting to finde out ſome that woulde beflowe charges vppon them, eſpecially ſuche as they had accuſtomed thereto,
<pb facs="tcp:9886:39"/>ſuch luſtie young ſouldiers of the citie as delighted in ſuch paſtime. Hee was (as I meane to tel you) betweene theſe wemen deuiſing and counterfaiting all kinde of brauerie, reciting more pleaſant and ſwéete wordes than euer <hi>Ouide</hi> wrote: but when they perceiued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> their beautie had vanquiſhed him cleane, and that hee was left without ſhame, they demanded of him their breakefaſt, and he therfore to haue the accuſtomed paiment. Wherupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hee bing as colde in the purrſe as he was hote in ſtomacke, fell in ſuche a traunce, that he loſt all the colour in his face: his toung not able to talke, was faine to alleage vaine excuſes. But they which in their ſcience were well inſtructed, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they perceiued his infirmitie, they gaue him ouer for ſuche a one as hee was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede. All this while I was breaking my faſt with ſtalkes of colworts, &amp; when I had done, like a diligent ſeruaunt, not ſeene of my maiſter, retourned home, meaning to ſweep ſome part of the houſe that hadde moſt neede: but I coulde not finde wherewithal to do the deed. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not knowing what to doe, I began
<pb facs="tcp:9886:40"/>in the worlde, that are in ſuch brauery as this my maſter is in, which doe ſuffer more for a little vaine glories ſake, than they would do for the loue of thée. I ſtoode in the doore ſo long remembring all thoſe things, that my maiſter paſſed thorow a long and narrow ſtreete, then I went in, and within a minute of an houre, I viſited the whole houſe aboue and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neat, without ſtaying, or finding wherat to ſtay. When I had made the vnlucky b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dde, I tooke my pot and went ſtreighte to the Riuer, and being ready to take vp my water, I might perceiue my maiſter in a Garden ouer the water, in greate talke with two comely women, whiche by their countenaunce ſeemed to be ſome of them, whereof in <hi>Toledo</hi> a number are rifely found: &amp; many of them take an vſe of going abroade carly in the morning in Sommer time, to take the ayre in thoſe Gardens, and to breake their faſte with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prouiſion of their owne vnder trees and ſhadowes, nere that pleaſant Riuer, truſting to finde out ſome that woulde beflowe charges vppon them, eſpecially ſuche as they had accuſtomed thereto,
<pb facs="tcp:9886:40"/>ſuch luſtie young ſouldiers of the citie as delighted in ſuch paſtime. Hee was (as I meane to tel you) betweene theſe wemen deuiſing and counterfaiting all kinde of brauerie, reciting more pleaſant and ſwéete wordes than euer <hi>Ouide</hi> wrote: but when they perceiued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> their beautie had vanquiſhed him cleane, and that hee was left without ſhame, they demanded of him their breakefaſt, and he therfore to haue the accuſtomed paiment. Wherupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hee bing as colde in the purrſe as he was hote in ſtomacke, fell in ſuche a traunce, that he loſt all the colour in his face: his toung not able to talke, was faine to alleage vaine excuſes. But they which in their ſcience were well inſtructed, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they perceiued his infirmitie, they gaue him ouer for ſuche a one as hee was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede. All this while I was breaking my faſt with ſtalkes of colworts, &amp; when I had done, like a diligent ſeruaunt, not ſeene of my maiſter, retourned home, meaning to ſweep ſome part of the houſe that hadde moſt neede: but I coulde not finde wherewithal to do the deed. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not knowing what to doe, I began
<pb facs="tcp:9886:41"/>to muſe wherin I ſhold occupy my ſelfe, maſter ſtudy, I determined to tary vntill noone, that my maſter came, for perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture hée woulde bring ſomethings with him for vs to eate: wherefore I taried his comming, yet all for nothing, for it was nowe two a cloc6ke, and bee not yet come: but becauſe hunger oppreſſed me ſore, I came out and locked the doore, laying the key where he had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded, with a lowe and a ſorrowfull voice, my handes thruſt into my boſome, I began to retourne to my former practiſe, in ſo much, that hauing GOD before myne eyes, and my toung, in his name, I fell to beg bread from dore to dore, and from houſe to houſe, where I thought beſt to ſpeede, hauing learned this trade in my ſucking yéeres, I meane with the blinde maiſter, I became ſuche a ſcholler, that although in that Citie there was ſmall charitie, nor the peace was not aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, yet notwithſtanding I had put my affaires in ſuche good order, that before the clocke ſtroke foure, I hadde layde a pound of bread in my belly, and twice as much in my hoſeme &amp; ſleeues. I returned
<pb facs="tcp:9886:41"/>then homewarde, and in my way wents thorowe the ſtreetes where they ſolde tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, wher I demanded a woman y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> was there hir charitie, ſhe gaue mee a piece of a neats foote, and a fewe ſodden tripes.</p>
            <p>When I came home, my curteouſe maſter was within, hauing folded his cloake &amp; laid it vp<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> walking vp and down the courte: and as ſoone as he did ſee me, he came towards me, wherefore I feared he would haue beaten me, becauſe I had laried ſo long, but it was not Gods will. The firſt thing he demaunded mee, was, wher I had bene? I anſwered, ſir I was here vntil it was two a clocke, and when I perceiued that your maiſterſhip came not, I went forth into the citie, to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende my ſelfe to good people, whiche haue giuen me thus much for gods ſake, and ſo ſhewed him the tripes whiche I kept in the ſkirt of my coate, whereat he made no angrie countenance, but fayde, I haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ried for thee to dinner, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I could not ſee thee come, I dined alone, as for thee, thou haſt done like an honeſt boy, for it is better to beg than to ſteale, as God helpe mee I am of that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion,
<pb facs="tcp:9886:42"/>one thing onely I will deſire thee to do, that thou wilt not let them knowe that thou doſt dwell with me, nor that I am thy maiſter: For that touched mine honor, and I do not doubte but that will be kept ſecret for very fewe do knowe me in this citie, I would to God I had neuer come to it. Of that matter ſir take you no care, ſayde I, for no man will aſke mée that queſtion, I néede not therefore make ſuch accompt to any of them. But why doeſt thou not fall nowe to thy vit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels poore foule, if it bee Gods will wee ſhall ſoone bee out of this miſerie: thou ſhalt vnderſtande, that ſithence I came in hither, I had neuer good houre, this houſe is ſurely built in an vnhappye place, and certainely ſome houſes are ſo vnluckye, that looke whoſoeuer doeth dwell within them, hee ſhall bee ſure to haue euill fortune. But I promiſe thee, that as ſoone as the moneth is ended, I will not dwell here, (no though they would giue it me rent free.) I fall downe then, and becauſe hee ſhoulde not thinke mée a couetous glutton, I drewe out my vittels, and there began to ſuppe honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb facs="tcp:9886:42"/>biting my tripes with my bread hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely, beholding diſſemblingly my mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable maiſter, which hadde his cye al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes vppon my ſkirte, beeing at that time my onely platter. God take ſuche compaſſion on mee, as I did then vppon him, for I had oftentimes endured, yea and daily felt that ſorrow, which I knew tormented him: wherefore I imagined with my ſelfe, how I might well inuire him: but becauſe he tolde me that he had dyned, I was afraide leaſt hee would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe the bankst. Finally, I wiſhed that the poore man wold haue eaſed his paine, by helpe of mine, and that he wold haue eaten with me for company, as hee had done the day before, eſpecially, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> then I had better vittels, and more ſtore, and moreouer that then my hunger was leſſe: it pleaſed God to accompliſhe my deſire and his together, for when as I had begon my meate, as hee walked hee came neere to me, ſaying, <hi>Lazaro</hi> I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe thee thou haſt the beſt grace in ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that euer I did ſee any man haue, for there is no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſéeth thée eate, but by ſeeing thee feede, ſhall haue appetite,
<pb facs="tcp:9886:43"/>I did pitie him, rather then hate him, for oftentimes with carying him home wherewith to paſſe the day, I felte griefs my ſelfe. One morning, the poore gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman roſe vp in his ſhirt, and went vp to the toppe of the houſe, to eaſe hun ſelfe, and in the meane ſeaſon to hée out of the ſuſpition that I was in, I vnfolded his dublet and his hoſe, which were his boulſter, and there founte a little purſe of veluet, which had a hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth wrinkels in it, but the deuill a peny, nor yet any<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtgne that there had bene any there long time before. Then did I ſay to my ſelfe, this man is poore, no man can giue that which hée hath not: but my couetous blind man, and my wretched prieſt, vnto whom God hath giuen ſo much goods, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one got with ſmoth hand, the other gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with his looſe toung, and yet they famiſhed mee continually: there was good reaſon why I ſhoulde hate ſuch peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſo is the cauſe, why this mans caſe ſhoulde be lamented. God knoweth that when I met with any of his eſtate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of like grauitie, pace, and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, howe I pitied them, thinking that
<pb facs="tcp:9886:43"/>they did endure that which I did ſée him daily ſuffer, whome I hadd rather ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for all his pouertie, than any of the other for the cauſes aboue named. I did like him well, but only y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> me thought he was to preſumptuous, where I often wiſhed that ſeeing hee ſo plainely perceiued his owne pouertie, hée wold ſomething haue hid his fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taſtical pride. But as I thinke, it is a ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon vſual rule amongſt ſuch as hée, which though they haue not a croſſe in the worlde, nor a Denier, the cappe muſt needes ſtande in his olde place: but if GOD of his mercie doe not order the matter, all ſuche are like to dye of that vile diſeaſe. As I continued in ſuche e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, ſuſtaining the life that I haue told you, my euill fortune which neuer ceaſed to purſue mee, woulde not yet ſuffer me to continue in that troubleſome and ſhamefull kinde of life. For the matter happened thus: the Lords of the counſell made proclamation with ſound of trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, becauſe that that yeare there was ſearcitie of corne, all poore people being ſtrangers, ſhould forſake the Citie, vpon paine that hee which from thencefoorthe
<pb facs="tcp:9886:44"/>ſhould be taken, ſhould be puniſhed with ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pes: and ſo exeruting the law, within th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> dayes after the pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> amatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I ſawe a whole proceſſion of poore folke whipped theough the foure principall ſtreetes, which ſight did ſo feare mee, that neuer after I durſt venture to beg. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might you haue ſéene a ſtrange diet we kep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at home, and the great ſilence that was there ſo that wée were conſtrained to faſte two or three dayes together, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out eating any morſell, or ſpeaking a woorde: and as for mee, the beſt ſhifte I made, was amongſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ertaine poore wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rden, which were ſpinners and cap knit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> my life, by reaſon of the aquaintance I had with them, being our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> neighbours: For of that meat they had I ſhould haue a litle, wherwith I did not ſo lament mine owne caſe, as I did my poore maiſters, which in eighto dayes did not ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e one morſell, at the leaſt, wee were ſo long at home without meate, but in deede I know not whether he went, nor what hée did eate abr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>, yet notwithſtanding, for all this, you
<pb facs="tcp:9886:44"/>ſhould ſee him come ſome times vp the ſtreete, with a bodie as large as any gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hounds of good race: and for to maintain his poore honor, hée was wonte to take a ſtraw in his hand, wherof alſo there was wante in our houſe,
<note place="margin">Small neede to picke his teeth for any meate he had e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ten.</note> and ſtanding with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the dore, would therewith picke thoſe which had little neede of picking, for any thing that had ſtucke in them with ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. Lamenting ſtill the vuluckineſſe of that houſe, he would ſay, it greueth me, to ſee how all our ſorrowe commeth of this houſe, thou ſeeſt howe vnconfortable and darke it is, and as long as we dwell here, wee are like to bee thus tormented, theré<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I woulde to God the moneth were ended, that wee might depart out of it. And as wee continued in this afflicted &amp; famiſhing perſecution, one day a rial en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into the power of my maſter,
<note place="margin">Sixe pence Engliſh.</note> I know not by what good lucke and adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, wherewith hee came home ſo blo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing,
<note place="margin">Belike ſome g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ers had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uen it him and it was full time.</note> as if he had brought with him the whole treaſure of Venice, and ſo with a mery and liuely countenance hee giueth it to mee, ſaying, take here <hi>Iazaro,</hi> nowe God beginneth to open his hande, and to
<pb facs="tcp:9886:45"/>ſmile vpon vs, goe quickly to the market place, and buy bread, wine and fleſh, that wee may breake the diuels enuious eye: and furthermore, bicauſe thou ſhalt haue good cauſe to reioyce, thou ſhalt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that I haue hired an other houſe, therfore, the moneth once ended, we will no longer abide in this miſerable vnluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ky houſe, curſed be it, and he that layde the firſt tile on it, for in euill time did I come in. By our lorde all the time that I haue bene here, I neuer dranke drop of wine, nor a morſell of fleſhe entred into my belly, nor yet haue I had any reſt in it, ſuche is the ſorrowe and miſerie that belongeth to it, goe thy wayes and make ſpeede, and let vs dine this daye like Earles. Then I tooke my riall and my pot, and with all haſte, I began to goe vp the ſtreete, towardes the market place, with ioy and mirth. But what profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth all this, nowe that I am borne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuche a planet that I can neuer en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioye any pleaſure long, without hyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draunce, (it appeareth ſo nowe) for as I went on my way, making my accounte howe I ſhould beſtowe my money vpon
<pb facs="tcp:9886:45"/>that which ſhould be moſt profitable and beſt, geuing infinite thanks to God (that he had giuen my maſter that money) vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſuddaine I mighte ſee right before me a dead coarſe come down the ſtreete, accompanied with many prieſtes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther people: I leaned to the wall to giue them place, and the coarſe went by, I might ſee a woman whiche belike was the dead mans wife, folowing the beere, all in mourning weede, acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panied with other women, and ſhe weeping and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting, ſaid: O my huſband &amp; my lord, alas, whether doe they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arie you? to the vnconfortable and ſad houſe, to the darke and ſorrowfull houſe, to the houſe where they neuer eate nor drinke? When I had heard her ſpeake theſe woordes, mée thought heauen and earth had met, and I ſaid, O vnfortunate wretch that I am; they carie this dead coarſe to our houſe: wherefore I forſooke my way, and brake in betweene the people, and running downe the ſtreete as faſt as euer I could, I got into the houſe, and when I had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred therein, I locked the doore with all haſte, calling out to my maiſter for
<pb facs="tcp:9886:46"/>ſtraunger long before, by reaſou that hée had ſo little acquaintance with thoſe of the Citie. Finally, my wiſh was accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, and I vnderſtoode that which I coueted to knowe: for vpon a day, after that hee had dyned reaſonably well, hee being at that time indifferently well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ed, declared vnto mee his affaires, in ſo much that hee certified mée, that he was borne in <hi>Caſtilia</hi> the old, and howe that hee had forſaken his countrye for nothing in the worlde, but becauſe hee would not abaſe him ſelf ſo much as put off his cappe to a Genleman his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: and hauing heard all his diſcourſe, I ſaid vnto him, ſir if he were ſuch a one as you ſay, and beſides that, if he were richer than you, it hadde beene but your duetie to put off your cappe firſt to him, for I beleeue he would haue done the like to you: in deede hee is a gentleman, and richer than I, and he would always put off his cap to the vttermoſt, when I did put off mine, but ſeeing that oftentimes mine was firſt off, reaſon would haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, that his ſhold once haue bin firſt, and ſo haue woon of me by quicke hand,
<pb facs="tcp:9886:46"/>the courteſſe. As for me ſaid I. I woulde neuer haue had regard to that. Thou art a childe ſaide he, and therefore thou kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt not what doeth belong to honoure, which at this daye is the onely refuge of ſuch as bee honeſt: therefore thou ſhalt vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that I am as thou ſeeſt a poore eſqire, and I make a vowe to God, that if I ſhould méete in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> midſt of the ſtréete an Earle, that wold not put his cap alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether off, as well as I do mine, the next time I ſée him come, I will enter into ſome houſe, as if I had ſome buſineſſe there, or elſe croſſe ouer into an other ſtréete, if there be any betweene mee and him, ſo that I ſhal not néede to put of my cappe to him, for a Gentleman is bound to none but to God and the Prince, and therefore it is reaſon that an honeſt man ſhall be curious to eſtéeme his owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone. I doe remember that vpon a day, I diſhonoured, and hadde almoſt beaten a crafts man where I was borne, becauſe that when ſo euer he met me, hee woulde ſay <hi>Mantenga deos a vim,</hi> which is to ſay, Sir, God maintaine your worſhip: I tooke him once with the déede, and ſaid,
<pb facs="tcp:9886:47"/>will ſtreght bid you fare well, and moſte commonly, their wages is payde with long termes, ſometime your meate and drinke onely for your painefull ſeruice. And when they meane to reforme their conſcience, and to conſider the ſeruaunts paine, there ſhall be deliuered out of the wardrobe, ſome cut dublet, or ſome thred bare cloake, or coate: but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a man ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth a Noble man of the Order, hee ſhal better paſſe ouer his miſerie: but perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture there is not in me abilitie to ſerue &amp; to content ſuch men. By God if I had met with one of them, I thinke certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I ſhoulde quickely haue bene chieſe of his counſel, for I would haue done him a thouſad kind of ſeruices. I could haue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled as well as any other, yea &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>efolde, that it wold haue ben maruellous, I woulde haue ſmiled merily at his doings, although they had not bene the beſt in the worlde, I would neuer haue recited that which ſhold haue diſpleaſed him, no although it had beene much for his profit, moſt diligent about his perſon in word &amp; dorde, neuer vering my ſelfe about the well doing of thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:9886:47"/>that ſhoulde neuer come to his ſight, but ſometimes haue chid ſuch as ſerued, wher he might heare mee, that I might ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me to be carefull, about that which touched him and whenſoeuer he ſhold happen to fall out with any of his men, then wold I put foorth two or three ſmooth wordes to ſet him forward, which ſhold ſeeme to be in the fauor of the offender, affirming al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes that which I thought he liked of: &amp; on the contrarie ſide, a malicious moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of the ignorant and rude ſorte: fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, I wold alwayes demande and procure, how to know the liues of ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, to account them vnto him, with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuchtricks of like qualitie which at this day are vſed in greate palaces and courts, and which pleaſe the chiefe dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers herein, which can not abide to ſee in their houſes vertuous men, but do abhor, &amp; eſteeme them as nought, deſpiſing &amp; cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them fooles, &amp; ignoraunt in the traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick of weight is affaires ſo that the Lord ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſafely truſt to their ſimple doings in weightie matters: therefore nowe a dayes, thoſe that are ſubtill and craftie, get into fauour, and vſe ſuch meanes as
<pb facs="tcp:9886:48"/>cheth vnto mee, and taking faſt holde on the coller of my coate, ſaide: thou arte priſoner, vnleſſe thou tell where thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter his goods are become: but as neuer no man had taken holde on mee in that place before ſauing onely my blinde ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, who neuer layde han<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e on mee ſo rudely, but ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, that I might leade him that could not ſee, I was afrayd, &amp; crying mercie, I promiſed to tell al that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded. Go to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſay they, ſay on gods name what thou knoweſt and bee not afraide: the Scriuener ſitteth downe in haſte, to write the Inuentorie, dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding what goods he had. I then began to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare what I knewe, ſaying, ſir, the goods that hee hath, or at leaſte that which he tolde me he had, was a piece of grounde, where foundation of houſes is layde, and moreouer a Doue houſe, which is faine, Wel ſaid (ſay they) my boy, though that be little worth, it is ſufficient to pay vs, In what place of the Citie ſtandeth it, (ſay they) I anſwered, mary it ſtandeth a good way hence in his owne countrey. The matter is then in a faire caſe (ſay they) but wher is his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey: he told me
<pb facs="tcp:9886:48"/>that he was borne in <hi>Caſtilia</hi> the old: the Sergeant, and the Scriuener, laughing apace, ſayde, this confeſſion is ſufficient for you to recouer the debte (though it were greater) the neighbours that were there preſent, ſaid, this childe is an inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and he hath not dwelt long with the Squire, therefore he knoweth no more of him than you doe, hee hath oftentymes come to vs, and we haue giuen him ſuch meate as we had, for Gods ſake, and at nightes gone in to lye with his maſter: when they perceiued my innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie, they did ſet me at libertie. The Sergeant and the Scriuener did demaund of the man &amp; the woman their fee, wherevppon there roſe great contention, and they alleaged that they were not bound to pay, ſeeing that there was no execution made, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rially, ſeeing there was not wherewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: the officers alleaged, for that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming thither, they had left vndone matters of muche greater importaunce: finally, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter many angrie wordes, a poore carier was loaden with the olde matteris, which was the womans, ſcante halfe a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dade to the bearer: then went they all
<pb facs="tcp:9886:49"/>flue out together chyding, what became of them after. I knowe not, I beléeue the poore mattris payde for all. And thus as I tel you, I loſt my third inaſter when as I fully perceiued euill fortune wrought altogether againſt mee, in ſo muche that my affairs went ſo back ward, that wher as maiſter eare wonte to bee forſaken of their ſeruants, it was not ſo with mee, but my maiſter was faine to forſake me, yea and runne away in haſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>How Lazaro placeth him ſelfe to dwell with a Frier of the Abbey of Grace.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Was then conſtrained to ſéeke the fourth maiſter, which was a Frier of the Abbey of Grace, vnto whome the poore women which I haue to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de you off, preferred mee. They called hym couſin. This man was an enemie to the Quire, not liking well of his meales in the couent, a man loſt for going abrode, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us to ſee worldly affaires and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitations,
<pb facs="tcp:9886:49"/>wherefore I thinke that hee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone did teare moe ſhoes than all the reſt of his brethren: it was hee that gaue mee the firſt ſhoes that euer I wore in all my life, which laſted mee but eighte dayes, for he neuer lefte trotting abroad: wherefore for this, and for other ſmall matters, which at this time I will not ſpeake of, I was faine to forſake him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>How Lazaro placeth him ſelfe with a Pardoner, and What things happened to him in his ſeruice.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Met by euil cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with the fifth maiſter, which was an vtterer of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons, the diſceitfulleſt marchant and the moſt ſham<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>leſſe, that euer I did ſée, or any man els: for to diſpatch away his pardons, hee had fine meanes and traficke, and daily ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined therefore moſt ſubtill inuentions. As ſoone as hee arriu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d to ſuch townes, were he ſhold vtter his pardons, he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld
<pb facs="tcp:9886:50"/>firſt preſent ſome gifte of ſmall value or ſubſtance to the Prieſts and Curates of that place: ſometimes a Cabadge lettis, a couple of Lemuio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or Oranges: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whiles an apricocke, or elſe a couple of Meaches, or at the leaſte, to euery one a faire Peare: and by that means he went about to make them his frends, that they mighte fauoure his affaires, and cauſe their pariſhioners to receiue the pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: yea, and that they ſhould thanke him, hee woulde alwayes bee informed bfore hee came, which were learned, &amp; which not. When he came to thoſe which he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood were learned, he woulde be ſure ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to ſpeake worde of latin, for feare of ſtumbling: but vſed in ſnche places, a gentle kinde of <hi>Caſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lian Spaniſh,</hi> his rong alwayes at libertie: and contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, whenſoeuer hée was informed of the reuerend <hi>Domines</hi> (I meane ſuch as are made prieſtes, more for money than for learning and good behauiour) to hear him ſpeake amongs ſuche men, you would ſaye it were S. Thomas: for hee woulde then, two houres together talke latin, at leſt which ſeemed to bee, though
<pb facs="tcp:9886:50"/>it was not. When that they receiued not his pardons friendly, hee ſought meanes to make them to take them perforce: ſo that oftentimes, hée herefore moleſted the pariſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oners, otherwhiles cauſing them to receiue them by ſubtile inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. And nowe, ſeeing that it were too long to accounte all ſuche partes as I did ſee him vſe. I will recite one, whereby he ſhe wed right wel how ſufficient he was. He had preached two or three dayes, in a village, within the dioceſſe of the Arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Toledo,</hi> without omitting any part of his accuſtomed diligence, and the people had not taken one pardon, nor no man (as farre as I coulde perceiue) was minded to receiue any: wherefore he was in great rage. And as he imagined what hée had beſte to doe,
<note place="margin">Pardoners haue alwayes with them a ſergeant to taky vp gages in ſuch houſes as refuſe to pay for their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the time appointed.</note> determined to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uite and byd all the people to come thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the next day, ſo to diſpatche his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ght after ſupper, he and his Sergeant wente to playe for theyr breakefaſt, and as they plaied, they fell at ſuch debate, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one gaue euill wordes to the other: In ſo much, that at the laſt hée ſayde to his Sergeant, that he was a
<pb facs="tcp:9886:51"/>thief, and the Sergeant anſwered, ſaying that he was a falſifier, wherefore the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſarie my maiſter layde hande vpon a ſhorte pike that ſtoode behinde the doore where they plaied, and the ſergeant on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſide, put hand to his ſworde which hong by his ſide, ſo that with the greate noyſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we made, our hoſt &amp; our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours came in, and went between them: then they beeing ſore angrie, ſought all meanes to come together, that the one might kill the other: but the houſe was ſo full of people, that they coulde by no meanes come nee to one another, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they neuer lefte, geuing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther iniurious wordes, in ſo muche that the Sergeant ſaid to my maiſter, that he was a faſifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, and that the Pardons which hee preached of daily, were moſte falſe. To be briefe, when the people per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued that they could by no meanes pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e them, they determined to carie the Sergeant away to an other lodging, and my maiſter remained ſtill there in great rage. Whereupon our hoſt, with his neighbours deſired him hartily that hee woulde forget his anger, and goe to bed;
<pb facs="tcp:9886:51"/>and ſo then we w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t all to ſléepe. As ſoone as day appeared in the morning, my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter went to the Church and cauſed them there to ring to Maſſe, &amp; to Sermon, that he might diſpatch his Pardons, then the people aſſembled together, murmuring amongſt them ſelues at the Pardone, ſaying that they were falſe and nothing worth, ſeeing that the Sergeant himſelfe had affirmed the ſame: So that before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time, they hauing ſmall minde to receiue any, they then vtterly abhorred them. Maſter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſarie mounte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h vp into the pulpit, and beginneth his ſermon, encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging the people not to forſake ſuche great goodneſſe and indulgence, as the holy pardon conteined: and being in the midſt of his ſermon, the ſerg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ant co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth in at the Church doore, and when that hée hadde ended his prayers, he roſe vp ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, and with a loude voyce diſcretely ſayde, ye honeſt &amp; godly people, giue ears that I may tell you a worde or two, and then heare whome yée will. I am come hither in the company of this crowe kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per which nowe preacheth, who hathe deceiued me, promiſing, that if I woulde
<pb facs="tcp:9886:52"/>helpe him in his affaires, I ſhoulde haue hal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the gaines. But now perceiuing the damage that my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hold receiue, and beſides that, the loſſe of your goods, I do earneſtly repent that which I haue done,
<note place="margin">All Sergeants in Spaine doe beare a white, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ndes, higher than the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues by half a foote as big<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s finger.</note> and I will tel you plainly, that the pardons which he hath brought, are falſe: therefore yee ought not to beleeue him, nor yet take any one of them. As for me, I will neither bee partaker with him, one waye or other, therefore from this time foreward, I doe forſake the rodde of them, which I nowe caſt to the grounde: for if hereafter hée bee puniſhed for his falſhoode, you may be witneſſe with mee that I am no doer with him herein, nor yet helpe him, but doe rather bewray vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you his craft and falſhood: and when he had ſaide all, certaine men of honour which were there, would néeds haue caſt him out of the Church,
<note place="margin">They were no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>rds, enerv <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>or there.</note> to auoide ſla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der: but my maſter did forbid them ſo to doe, commaunding them all vppon payne of excommunication, to ſuffer him to ſaye all that euer hee coulde, and hee him ſelfe kept Silence whyles that the Sergeants declared al that which I haue rehearſed:
<pb facs="tcp:9886:52"/>and as ſoone as hee helde his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ounge, my maſter demanding hun whether he wold ſay any more: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſergeant anſwered, there may bee much more ſaide of thée, and of thy falſhoode, but at this time this is ſufficient. Then my maſter commiſſarie falling downe vpon his knees in the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, holding vp his handes, his eyes l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vp to heauen ſayde theſe words: O Lorde God, from whom nothing is hid, vnto whome all things are manifeſt, and vnto whome nothing is vnpoſſible, who ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do all things, thou knoweſt the truth, and how vniuſtly I am accuſed and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered: as for me (O lord) I forgiue him, that thou mayſt forgiue me. Haue no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde to hun that knoweth not what he doeth nor ſaieth: notwithſtanding, O Lord, I do beſéech thee: &amp; through iuſtice I demaunde of thee, that thou wilt not diſſemble this iniurie which is done vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, peraduenture, ſome that are heere preſent, were minded to take th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s diuine pardon, which now will not, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing place and credite to the wicked mans words: and becauſe this matter is ſo hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tfull to Chriſtian neighbours, I
<pb facs="tcp:9886:53"/>beſéech thee once againe good Lorde, that thou wilt not diſſemble it, but immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that it may pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſe thée to ſhewe here a miracle, and that it may be thus: If it be true that this man ſaith, that is, that the Pardons which I haue heere are falſe, that this pulpit maye then ſinke with mee, as farre as the depth of ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uen men vnder the grounde, that neither it nor I may neuer bee ſéene againe. And on the other ſide, if that bee true which I ſay, that he beeing perſwaded by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, hath ſaide theſe words falſly and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truly, only to depriue the people of ſuche goodneſſe, that then it maye alſo pleaſe thee to puniſh him, that his malicious peruerſitie may bee knowen to all men. My de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>out maiſter had ſcant ended his prayers, but that the poore Sergeant fell in a traunce, giuing him ſelfe ſuche a blowe againſt the ground, that all the Church ſounded of it, ſtretching out his body with great abſidance of fome at his mouth, making ſtraunge viſages, and ſtriking the ground both with hande and foote, tumbling vp and downe from one ſide to an other: In ſo muche that the
<pb facs="tcp:9886:53"/>noiſe which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people made, was ſo great, that one could not heare another. Some were amazed and ſore afraid, ſaying God be his helpe, and other ſaide, hee hath that which hee hath deſerued, ſeeing that hee durſt affirme ſuch falſhod. Finally ſome of thoſe that were there, which to my iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t were not without great feare, came néere to hold faſt his hands, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with hee ſtroake all ſuche as came neere him. Others helde him falſte by the féete, for there was neuer falſe moyle in the world that euer kicked ſo faſt: and ſo they held him a good while. Ther were aboue xv. men vpon him, and he gaue them all their hands ful: ſo that if they had forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten their buſineſſe, he woulde haue giuen ſome of them ouerwhart the teeth. All this while my maiſter was in the pulpit vpon his knees, holding his handes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſtill, his eyes bent towards heane<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, tranſported into ſuch diuine eſſence, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> all the noyſe and rumour which was in the Church, was not ſufficient to bring him out of his diuine contemelation. Certain honeſt men that were there, came vnto him, and a waked him by force of crying,
<pb facs="tcp:9886:54"/>God (ſeeing that he deſireth not the death of a ſinner, but rather that hee ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and liue) to pardon, forgiue and reſtore to life, that poore ſinner which was led by the deuill, ouercome with death and ſinne, that he might repent and confeſſe his ſinn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>: when hee had ſo done, he ſent for one of the pardons, and laide it vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his head, wherupon immediatly the poore Sergeant began to amende and by little and little to retourne to him ſelfe. And as ſoone as he had recouered his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, he knele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h dow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> at maiſter commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries feete, &amp; there demanded pardon, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing how that he had ſaid and done all thoſe things, by the mouth and inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the deuill, as well to giue him griefe, and to be reuenged of him, as alſo d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                  <desc>••••••</desc>
               </gap>ſe the deuill was ſorie to ſée the goodneſſe which people receiued by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the holy pardons. My maſter did then forgiue him, and friendſhippe was made betweene them. Then was there ſuche greate haſte to take the pardons, that almoſte no creature liuing in that towne, but tooke one, the huſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ande, and the wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, ſounes and daughters, menns
<pb facs="tcp:9886:54"/>ſeruantes and maid ſeruants, there was none but woulde haue one. This newes was ſpred abroad through al the townes there about, ſo that we then ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ued thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it was not needefull to preache, nor yet to goe to the Churche to diſpatche the Pardons: for the people came ſo fafte to our lodging for them, as if they had bene peares that had bene giuen them for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: in ſo muche that my maiſter diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched and vttered away ten or twelue thouſand pardons in ten or twelue little villages thereabouts, without preaching one ſermon. And as for my part, I will confeſſe my ignoraunce, for when this their inuention was tried, I was in a gret maruell to ſee ſuch a ſtraunge caſe, &amp; I thought the matter had bin ſo in deed, as many other did: yet notwithſtanding, when I perceiued once the Ieſting and ſcoffing that my maſter &amp; the Sergeent would make at the matter by the waye, I vnderſtood plainely, that all that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfaite ſhewe was inuented by my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſubtile induſtrious arte. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I was of tender yeres, yet I toke great pleaſure to conſider their doings,
<pb facs="tcp:9886:55"/>and would ſay to my ſelfe: Howe many are there ſuche as theſe that deceiue the ſimple people. To conclude, I continued with this fifte maiſter neere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oure mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethes, during which time I ſuffered much ſorrowe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>How Lazaro dwelleth with a Chaplaine, and what happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to him in his ſeruice.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fterward I entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſeruice of a pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Orummes, vnto whome I tempered co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, with whome I ſuffered a thouſand e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils, and as I was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of good bigneſſe, entring one daye into the great Church, one of the Chaplaines receiued me for his owne, and gaue mee in gouernment an Aſſe, with foure great tankerdes, and a whippe, to ſell water vp and downe the Citie, and this was the firſt ſtaire I climbed vp, to come to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb facs="tcp:9886:55"/>vnto good life:
<note place="margin">They do ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> water vp and downe the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to ſell vp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Aſſes, with foure &amp; ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> times ſixe ran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> kards: for the haue no wat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but from the riuer.</note> for my mouth had then the meaſure. I deliuered vp daily to my maſter in game thirtie <hi>Mareuedis,</hi> &amp; on euery Saturday I laboured for my ſelfe, and all the weeke alſo whatſoeuer I coulde earne ouer thirtie <hi>Mareuedis</hi> a day, was mine owne. This office was ſo good, that at foure yéeres ende I had ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with my wages and my gaines, ſo muche as bought mee apparell honeſtly, with old ſtuffe, whereof I bought an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> black fuſtian dublet, and a coate thréed bare with gathered ſtéeues and whol before, and a cloake that had bene of ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zado, and a ſworde of the olde making one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt of <hi>Cuellar.</hi> And perceiuin, my ſelfe then in apparell like an honeſ man, I deſired my maſter to take his Aſſe againe, and that I would no more follow that office. (⁂)</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:9886:56"/>
            <head>The Spaniardes life. Howe Lazaro dwelleth with a Sergeant, and what happened to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his ſeruice.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that I had taken my leaue of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chaplain I did place my ſelfe w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> a ſergeant, to be a mé<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of iuſtice: but I dwelled fewe dayes w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> him, for in ſhort time I perciued that it was a dangerous office,
<note place="margin">A man may ſcap in Spaine the hands of the officers of Inſtice if they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> flee into ſome church ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</note> eſpecially when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> certain tranſgreſſours, which retired into a Churche, chaſed my maſter &amp; me maruellouſly with ſtones &amp; ſtaues: and at that preſent time my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter (whom I taried for) was euil ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dled but they could neuer ouertake mee: yet for al that I did forſweare the office. And as I imagined what kinde of life I had beſt leade, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I might prouide ſome thing againſt mine olde age. God by his grace lightned my minde to finde out the profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table way: So that through the fauour which I had of my friends and maiſters, all the forrowes, which before that time I had ſuſtained, were recompenced with
<pb facs="tcp:9886:56"/>an office royall, which I obteined: the which I pretended, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> at this day there is no account but of them that haue wherewithall. So that at this preſent, I liue in mine office, &amp; exerciſe it to Gods ſeruice &amp; yours. Sir, it is ſo that I haue the charge to cry the wines that are ſold in this citic, and to make inquiraunce,
<note place="margin">The Cryers in Spaine doe fell at kinde of ſtufte and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y is whip. through the crie goeth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring with loude voyce what he hath done.</note> with open crye, for things that hour bene loſte, and when any ſuffer perſerution by iuſtice, I do accompanie them, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with loud voyce their offence. I am (in plain language) a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon cryer. Sir matters haue ſo well gone forewarde with me, &amp; I haue vſed my ſelfe ſo well, that in manner all things belonging to the office, paſſe through my hands. In ſo much, that looke whoſoeuer within this citte doth broch wine, or ſell any things, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Lazarillo de Tormes</hi> bee not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente, they make accounte neuer to get game. In this meane time, maſter Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon of ſaint <hi>Saluador</hi> your friend and ſeruaunt at commaundement, hauing knowledge of my perſon and habilitie, eſpecially ſince I had cryed his wyne, went about to marry me with his mayd.
<pb facs="tcp:9886:57"/>And after that I had conſidered, that with hauing to doe with ſuch a man as maſter Archdeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was, I cold not receiue but honeſtie and goodneſſe, I determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to doe it, ſo that I tooke her to wife, whereof hitherto I doe not repente: for beſides that ſhee is honeſt, and a diligent wench, I finde great fauour and helpe at maſter Archdec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns hand, for euery yéere from one tune to an other, hee giueth her as good as a loade of wheat, and againſt Chriſtmas or Eaſter, ſome good morſell of fleſhe, a couple or two of loaues, and ſuch old hoſe as he leaueth: and he cauſed vs to hier a little houſe neere his dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: on euery ſonday &amp; holy day we dined (moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly) in his owne houſe. But euill tongues which neuer ceaſe, woulde not ſuffer vs to liue in peace, they would ſay this and that, and that they did ſee my wife goe and make his bed, and dreſſe his meate. But God helpe them better than they ſay truthe. Forbeſides that ſhee is a woman that deeth not delighte in ſuche game, maiſter Archdeacon hath promiſed mee that whiche I truſte hée will fulfill. For vpon a time in her preſence, he ſaide
<pb facs="tcp:9886:57"/>at large vnto me, <hi>Lazaro de Tormes,</hi> he that will haue regarde to cuill tongues, ſhall neuer get profite. I ſay thus much vnto thée, I can neuer maruell, thoughe ſome men murmure to ſée thy wife come in an out of my houſe, which doing, I promiſe thée, ſhall not otherwiſe redcund but to thy great honeſtie and hers. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let people haue their woordes, haue thou onely regarde to that which ſhall be for thy profite. I anſwered him, ſaying, Syr, I haue determined to ioyne my ſelfe with thoſe that are good, but truth it is, that certaine of my friendes haue warned me of this, yea &amp; moreouer they haue twice or thrice certified mée wtih other, that before ſhe was maried to mee ſhée had two or thrée children, be it ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder your maiſterſhippes correction, ſéeing that ſhée is preſent. My wife be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan then to giue ſuch othes, that I thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght the houſe woulde haue ſuncke with vs all, and then beganne to wéepe, cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the time that euer ſhe married mée, in ſo much that I wiſhed my ſelfe dead when that I let ſcape that worde out of my mouthe. But I on the one ſide, and
<pb facs="tcp:9886:58"/>my maiſter on another, ſaid ſo much, that ſhe lefte weeping: and I did ſweare vnto her, that as long as I liued I woulde neuer againe vſe the like talke: and how that I reioyced and was well contente, that the ſhould come in and out both day and nighte, ſeeing that her honeſtie and faithfulneſſe was ſo well knowne. So the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we remained al thrée with one accord vntill this day, and neuer no man heard vs ſithence reaſon of that matter. And from that time forwarde, whenſoeuer I could happen to heare any man talk of this, I would ſtreight break off his mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſaye vnto him, looke if thou bee my friende, ſpeake nothing that ſhall grieue me, for I do not take him for my friende that cauſed me to ſorowe, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally that goeth about to ſowe diſcord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene mee and my wife, which I loue better than any thing in this world, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering howe that by her meanes, God hath done more for mee, than I haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, and I dare ſweare by the holy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, that ſhee is as honeſt a woman as any that dwelleth within the foure gates of <hi>Toledo:</hi> and hée that ſayeth the
<pb facs="tcp:9886:58"/>contrarie. I will beſtowe my life vpon him. So from thence foreward, they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner durſt meue any ſuch matter vnto me, &amp; I had peace alwayes in my houſe. This was the ſame yéere that our victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Emperour entred into this noble citie of <hi>Toledo,</hi> wher his court was kept with great feaſtes and triumphes, as your maſterſhip hath heard: finally, it was then that I was in my proſperitie, and in my chiefeſt time of good aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:9886:59"/>
            <head>The Spaniardes life. Laziro declareth the frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dſhip that certain high Duchmen ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, and what hapned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene them.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing now in the toppe of my proſperitie, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing fortune my friend, I neuer went without a bottle of the beſte wine in the citie, of the verie ſame I caried about me (beings commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> crier) to giue a taſte to as many as were willing to buy: by vertue of whiche wine I purchaſed ſo many gentlemen my friendes, as well inhabitaunts there as ſtrangers, that where ſo euer I came, the doore ſhoulde ſtreight bee opened for mee. And I was in fauoured euerie where, that if I had chaunced to haue ſlayne a man, or to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit ſome haynous offence, all the worlde woulde ſtreight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes haue bene on my ſide, being aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that thoſe gentlemen being the kings garde would ſufficiently both ſuccour &amp; helpe mee. Therefore when ſo euer wee
<pb facs="tcp:9886:59"/>met, I neuer ſuffered them to departe drimouthed away, but did carry the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with mée to the beſt wine I hadde broched in the citie, where oftentimes we went in vpon our own féete, and came out either without any, or at the leaſt with ſtrange féete.</p>
            <p>And that which I liked beſt of all, was that all the time I kept them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, the diuel a blanke <hi>Lazaro de for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes</hi> did pay, nor that they would conſent he ſhould pay: for whenſoeuer I did put my hande to my purſe (for manners ſake only) they would take it in euil part, and beholding me angerly, would ſay, <hi>Nitte Nitte, Aſticot lanz,</hi> and ſo reprehenting me, wold alleage, that where they wer in company no man ſhoulde pay a blanke: wherefore I was greatly in loue with theſe people: and it was not only that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued our turne, but as often as we mette we ſhould haue alſo ſlices of baco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, pieces of legges of mutton ſod in that pleaſant wine, with all manner of fine ſpice, and therewith they wold fill both my boſome and ſkirts, enough for my wife and mee a whole wéeke. The worlde beeing then
<pb facs="tcp:9886:60"/>ſo plentifull I would call to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance the hungrie fits I had ſuſteined in times paſt, prayſing the Lorde, and giuing him thanks that the world now at the length was ſo well changed. But as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe ſaith: He that will do good to thée, will either go his way, or die. And ſo it happened to me, the court remouing as it is wont to doe, and my friendes follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing it, at their departing I was defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by them that I woulde beare them companie, promiſing to ſhewe me much friendſhip and fauour. But remembring the olde prouerbe: Better is the euill knowns, than the good which is yet to knowe, thanking them for their good will, and deſiring their fauour, after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſighes and ſorrowfull embracings, I tooke my leaue, and they departed. And truly had I bene vnmaried, I would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue ſo forſaken their companie, for indeede they were people, muche of my nature and diſpoſition. And it was a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, and not a phantaſticall nor a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous life they did leade. A man ſhould neuer ſée the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcrupulous nor nice to enter into a tauerne, but would go in
<pb facs="tcp:9886:60"/>boldely (yea with cappe in hande) if the wyne for goodneſſe deſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rd ſo muche. They ware plaine men, ful of at honeſtie and gentle curteſie, and ſe well proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at all tunes, that I woulde to God when I am athueſt, I might alwayes meete with ſuch men. Notwithſtanding the loue which I bare to my wee and to my contrey (which newe I take for mine owne natrue, becauſe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n to commonly ſay, whence art thou honeſt man) cauſed me to ſtay at home. So I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued euer ſince in this citie, leading a ſolitarie life for the loſſe of my friendes and courtle life although that I was well knowen of all the citizens. Afterwardes I liued very well at mine owne eaſe, with en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of ioy and kinred, for the birth of a trim little daughter, which within a little whyle after my wyfe broughte foorth. Wherat I hauing ſome euill ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhe did ſwear al othes, that I was the father, and that ſhee was mine. I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in this eſtate, vntill that fortune thought that ſhe had nowe giuen me too much-eaſe, and that ſhee thought it rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for her to turne backe and ſhewe mée
<pb facs="tcp:9886:61"/>againe her ſeuere and cruell viſage, to temper thoſe fewe yéeres which I paſſed at eaſe, with as muche more trauell and deadly ſorowe, which nowe I ſhoulde endure. (O great God) who is able to write ſo vnfortunate &amp; miſerable a caſe, but muſt let the Inkhorne reſte and put the penne to his eyes?</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>¶ To the Reader.</head>
            <l>
               <hi>THough truth do purchaſe hate,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>and gloſing beare the bell:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Yet is the man to be belikte</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>that trueſt tale doth tell,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Without reſpect of place,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>of countrie, or of kinde:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>For ſo the law of writing doth</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>eche honeſt writer binde:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Then Lazaro deſerues</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>no blame, but praiſe to gaine,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>That plainly pens the Spaniards prank</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>and how they liue in Spaine.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>He ſettes them out to ſhewe</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>for all the world to ſee,</hi>
            </l>
            <pb facs="tcp:9886:61"/>
            <l>
               <hi>That Spaine when all is done, is Spaine</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>and what thoſe gallants be.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>The writer meant but well,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>and he that tooke the paine,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>To turne it to our mother tongue,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>the readers thankes would gaine</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>For all his former toyle,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>in penning of the booke,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>The ſuite is ſmall, allow him that,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>that hapſt hereon to looke.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Though ſmall the volume be,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>the value may be great:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Wherefore to yeeld him thy good will</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>let this my muſe entreat:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Let <hi>Roulande</hi> haue reward</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>for this his taken paine:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>And ſo thou (reader) mayeſt perhaps</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>the like hereafter gaine.</hi>
            </l>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. Turbeuile Gent.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>¶ Imprinted at London <hi>by Abell Ieffes.</hi> 1586.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
